<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Abridgment of the prerogatives of St. Ann, mother of the mother of God with the approbation of the doctors at Paris, and thence done into English to accompany The contemplations on the life and glory of Holy Mary, and the defence of the same, with some pieces of a like nature : to which a preface is added concerning the original of the story.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23680</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A108</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6614</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11966634</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11966634</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51732</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23680)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51732)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 46:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Abridgment of the prerogatives of St. Ann, mother of the mother of God with the approbation of the doctors at Paris, and thence done into English to accompany The contemplations on the life and glory of Holy Mary, and the defence of the same, with some pieces of a like nature : to which a preface is added concerning the original of the story.</title>
                  <author>Cross, John, 1630-1689. Contemplations on the life and glory of Holy Mary the mother of Jesus.</author>
                  <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], xv, [6], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Chitwell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Imprimatur ... Feb. l4, 1687. Guil. Needham ... D.D. Wilhelmo ..."</note>
                  <note>Translation and preface ascribed to William Clagett.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anne --  (Mother of the Virgin Mary), Saint.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51732:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51732:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ABRIDGMENT OF THE PREROGATIVES OF S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> ANN, MOTHER of the MOTHER of GOD.</p>
            <p>With the Approbation of the Doctors at <hi>Paris:</hi> And Thence Done into Engliſh to accompany <hi>The Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations on the Life and Glory of Holy</hi> MARY; and the Defence of the Same; with ſome Pieces of a like nature.</p>
            <p>To which a PREFACE is added concerning the Original of the STORY.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>IMPRIMATUR,</p>
                        <p>Liber cui Titulus, [<hi>An Abridgment of the Prerogatives of S.</hi> Ann, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Guil. Needham</hi> R. R. in Chriſto P. ac D.D. Wilhelmo Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiep. Cant. a Sacr. Dom.</signed>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Feb.</hi> 14. 1687.</date>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. <abbr>MDCLXXXVIII.</abbr>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:51732:2"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:51732:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THat Article of the Paſtoral Letter of Cardinal <hi>Camus,</hi> which directs his Clergy not to diſguiſe or miſrepreſent the Doctrine of the Church, as it ſhews the ingenuity of that Illuſtrious Prelate, ſo it manifeſtly detects, that he thought ſuch Artifices were not unuſual. I know that Ingenuity and fair Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting are what all will commend, but what few can bear, and as few practice. There is an Order of men whoſe Talent is generally thought not to lye much that way, who ceaſe not with all imaginable vigour to proſecute the giver of ſo Peſtilent Advice. Nor is it indeed ſtrange, that <hi>Dexterity</hi> ſhould be looked on as more advantagious to a Party, than naked <hi>Honeſty.</hi> But I muſt needs ſay, tho ſome have played more <hi>cunningly,</hi> there are others who have dealt more <hi>honeſtly;</hi> among whom I place the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templator</hi> on the <hi>Life of H.</hi> Mary: For this Gentleman deals plainly enough with the World, and gives ſuch a Pattern of Devotion towards the <hi>Queen,</hi> as ſhe is call'd, <hi>of all pure Creatures,</hi> as ſhews he is not aſhamed to bring into the greateſt <hi>Light,</hi> what others at the ſame time induſtriouſly caſt into <hi>Shadow.</hi> And having ſhew'd himſelf ſo very fair and open, I expected he would have before this time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the office of the following Treatiſe; and that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſaid ſo much of the <hi>Maternity</hi> of Holy <hi>Mary,</hi> he muſt have more than a little left for the <hi>Maternity</hi> of St. <hi>Anne.</hi> For if both (according to him, and the <hi>Maids</hi> of St. <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi>)
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:51732:3"/>the Tree is known by its Fruit, and the <hi>Branches</hi> are holy if the <hi>Root</hi> be ſanctified; therefore if <hi>Jeſus</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely Holy, <hi>Mary's</hi> fleſh was never defil'd, and if not <hi>Marys,</hi> neither St. <hi>Anns:</hi> If ſo, I ſay St. <hi>Ann</hi> has good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to complain of <hi>her</hi> being paſſed over with ſuch ſilence, while ſo great <hi>Adorations</hi> are paid to her <hi>Daughter.</hi> And if it look like <hi>Proteſtant</hi>-preſumption to go to God the Father only through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> without the Interceſſion of his <hi>Mother,</hi> it muſt needs be <hi>leſs</hi> Preſumption, and greater Humility, to beg the <hi>Grandmother</hi> too to intercede. If we can go ſo far, as to ſuſpect the efficacy of our Prayers, when offered up in the <hi>ſole</hi> Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and think it ſafeſt to recurr to the <hi>Divine Maternity,</hi> and the Name of <hi>Mary,</hi> it muſt needs be the beſt way to make them throughly effectual to follow the Advice of the <hi>Joſephine Maids,</hi> and in the firſt place to addreſs our ſelves to St. <hi>Ann,</hi> and in her name approach to the <hi>Daughter,</hi> who to be ſure is not able to refuſe her <hi>Mother</hi> any thing, no more than her <hi>Son</hi> can <hi>her.</hi> Nay, if we go to St. <hi>Anns</hi> Mother, it will be ſo much the better yet, and the ſame Reaſon would ſtill carry us higher till we can go no farther. The <hi>Principles</hi> are plainly own'd, and expreſly and induſtriouſly taught; and then it muſt be ſomewhat too like foulneſs to deny evident and palpable <hi>Conſequences:</hi> But I am ſo charitable as to think that the <hi>Contemplator</hi> on H. <hi>Mary,</hi> who has ſo Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphical a Pen in deſcribing her <hi>Honours</hi> and <hi>Glories,</hi> is juſt to his <hi>Principles;</hi> and if ſo, none can be fitter to extol the <hi>Prerogatives</hi> of her <hi>Mother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For we are told from Apocryphal Writers, and his own fruitful Imagination, of the ſtrange wonders of <hi>Maries Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 26, 28.</note> How ſhe was exempted from the general Curſe of Sin in her <hi>Paſſive Conception</hi> in the Womb of S. <hi>Ann;</hi> how ſhe had the uſe of Reaſon while there; underſtood the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and Decrees of God; ſaw into all the Myſteries of Grace; exerciſed Acts of a moſt pure, inflam'd and reſtleſs
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:51732:3"/>Love, and ſung a joyful <hi>Magnificat</hi> to her wonderful Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor. We are told how the
<note n="(a)" place="margin">P. 29.</note> Angels ſung, <hi>Glory be to the Mother of God;</hi> and then it cannot be otherwiſe, but that ſhe who is thus <hi>early</hi> complemented Queen of Heaven, muſt at her
<note n="(b)" place="margin">P. 45.</note> 
               <hi>Nativity</hi> be adorn'd with all inward and outward Graces, and have a moſt harmonious Body and Soul, upon which we muſt believe, that <hi>Heaven, Limbo</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> were repleniſh'd with tranſcendent Joys: We are after this told, how
<note n="(c)" place="margin">P. 52.</note> from the hour of her Birth ſhe makes a Vow, and at Three years end performs it;
<note n="(d)" place="margin">P. 54.</note> how ſhe is receiv'd into the Temple, and plac'd on the ſteps, on each of which ſhe ſings forth a Gradual Pſalm, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templates on the ſeveral Myſteries of the <hi>Roſary,</hi> and then begs the Chief Prieſt to be admitted into the Society of the <hi>Holy Women</hi> who watch'd and pray'd by the Ark; how her whole Life, both in the Temple and afterward, is only
<note n="(e)" place="margin">P. 80.</note> one continued act of <hi>ſuper-eminent</hi> Contemplation and Extaſy, with which at laſt ſhe is caſt into a <hi>Feaver</hi> of Love, which cauſes her death, upon which her Soul is conveyed with ineffable Harmonies of Angels, and ſeated in Glory above all their Quires, and
<note n="(f)" place="margin">P. 83.</note> her Body aſſum'd up af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, and veſted with Super-Seraphical Majeſty; and
<note n="(g)" place="margin">P. 90.</note> how the Angels and Elect ſeverally do <hi>homage</hi> to her; how the <hi>Angels</hi> give her the Badges of Soveraignty over <hi>Men, Archangels,</hi> over <hi>Nobles, Thrones,</hi> over <hi>Kings,</hi> and ſo the reſt; and how ſolemnly the Bleſſed Trinity congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates her; and all this is as particularly and exactly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd, as if he had been no leſs than Maſter of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</p>
            <p>It's pity the Scriptures ſhould be ſo ſcanty and imperfect, as to have none of this rare ſtuff; but our <hi>Joſephine</hi> Maids, who give the reaſon for the ſilence of the Evangeliſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their great <hi>Patroneſs,</hi> may give the ſame, why ſo little is ſaid by them concerning her <hi>Daughter,</hi> viz. That God <hi>conceals</hi> the greateſt Excellencies, and that the holieſt
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:51732:4"/>Saints are <hi>loſt</hi> to the World through the <hi>exceſs</hi> of their <hi>Merit;</hi> that <hi>Mary</hi> being the Soul that neareſt approach'd to the Divinity, was a Treaſure as <hi>ineffable</hi> as God; but that, God hath at length been pleaſed to draw theſe things out of ſilence by <hi>Annual Commemorations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as many as reaſon freely, cannot but have ſome ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion of the late uſhering theſe Commemorations into the Kalendar, and be apt to gueſs at the true Reaſon of the ſilence of the Holy Penmen, and conclude, the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit foreſeeing that ſuperſtitious worſhip that was to come into the World, to undermine the glorious deſigns of this Bleſſed Religion, took away whatever might prove the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions.</p>
            <p>The Enemy of Mankind was ſoon ſenſible of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion the Holy Ghoſt had made againſt the ſuperſtition which he deſign'd to introduce into the Church, and therefore early ſat his Inſtruments at work to prepare Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials. Goſpels were forg'd, and put forth under the name of Apoſtles, containing a Doctrine totally repugnant to theirs. Nor could Satan ever have a more cunning device to weaken and depreciate thoſe Inſtruments of our Salvation deliver'd to us by God, than this of <hi>coining</hi> others; For by giving falſe Scriptures, not only thoſe were impoſed upon who were not able to diſcover the Cheat, but, afterward when the Doctrine had taken ſome root, even thoſe that could; it being then very <hi>hard</hi> (if not <hi>impoſſible</hi>) ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorily to learn (other Authors of the ſame times, and of thoſe immediately ſubſequent mentioning the ſame things) how much, or what is to be credited in ſuch Writings, eſpecially if ancient. For very frequently, after the Piece has appear'd to be a Forgery, the Matter of it has not been disbelieved, even by Learned Men, but kept its ground upon the Authority of other Writers, who were but <hi>Copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> of that Condemn'd <hi>Original.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="v" facs="tcp:51732:4"/>
            <p>We have an Example of this in the very Caſe of the B. Virgin and her Mother, who continue ſtill to have thoſe Worſhips and Invocations made to them, whoſe probable Foundation is rejected even by the ſtiffeſt Aſſerters of their <hi>Prerogatives;</hi> for there being ſo very little ſaid of the One, and nothing at all of the Other, in the received Goſpels; our great Enemy, toward the accompliſhment of his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Deſign, was not negligent to ſupply that ſeeming Defect: And how could this be better done, than under the Name of S. <hi>James</hi> the <hi>Couſin</hi> or <hi>Brother</hi> of our Lord, who being of the ſame Family, can't but be ſuppoſed well acquainted with what he relates. This ſeems to be the main Original for ſuper-inducing ſuch a Devotion; and the whole Fabrick of the <hi>Marian</hi> Religion appears to lean upon no better Support: But notwithſtanding the Diſcovery of the Forgery, <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13th thought fit by his
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1584.</note> 
               <hi>Breve,</hi> to give S. <hi>Ann</hi> a Feſtival on the 26th of <hi>July;</hi> and <hi>Sixtus</hi> 5. Reforming the <hi>Breviary,</hi> appointed an Order to it; which was the occaſion of the Eſtabliſhment of the <hi>Maids of S. Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> who upon the keeping this Day, formed themſelves into a Family, taking S. <hi>Ann</hi> for their Patroneſs, and were afterwards confirmed, and taken into the Protection of the late Queen-Mother of <hi>France, Ann</hi> of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> So that in this Age the <hi>Mother</hi> of the Bleſſed Virgin is drawn out of Silence by a Feſtival of the Church; and the next Age may find perhaps another Feſtival even for <hi>Her</hi> Mother.</p>
            <p>I cannot find ſo much as the Names of <hi>Joachim</hi> and <hi>Ann</hi> before <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> who indeed
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Haereſ. 78. p. 1049. Ed. Paris 1622.</note> mentions them, and no more; nor is his Authority conſiderable enough to eſtabliſh any thing. S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Contra Fauſtum l. 23. To. 6. p. 98. Paris 1555.</note> writing againſt <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> doth not ſeem ſatisfied even as to this: and gives the ſame Reaſon that a Proteſtant would, which is its Uncanonicalneſs; <hi>Quia Canonicum non eſt, non me conſtringit,</hi> ſaith the Father. The
<note n="(d)" place="margin">De Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Virginis, To. 9. par. 3.</note> Epiſtle to <hi>Chromatius,</hi> concerning the <hi>Nativity of the Virgin,</hi> which is at the end of S. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s Works, is no
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:51732:5"/>leſs than that other of the ſame ſtamp concerning her
<note n="(a)" place="margin">De Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione B. V.</note> 
               <hi>Aſſumption,</hi> ſpurious; and is ſo condemned by <hi>Baronius,</hi> having been ſo firſt by <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> and ſince by all generally, except <hi>Chr. a Caſtro.</hi> Yet this and the <hi>Prot-evangelium</hi> are the incomparable Pieces that have had ſo many Copiers. It is not eaſie to determine of what Antiquity the Forgery is, but how great ſoever that be, there appear no Signs, but ſuch as are very late, of its being much credited. <hi>Germanus, Hippolytus,</hi> and <hi>Damaſcene</hi> ſay a little; but the Story is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry naked, till
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Lib. 1. c. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Nicephorus</hi> that lying Monk dreſſes it; and even that is very ſhort. The counterfeit S. <hi>Hierom</hi> tells a long Tale with ſuch a grace, as to make it doubtful who deſerves the Bell, he or the counterfeit S. <hi>James;</hi> they look like two ſuch <hi>inimitable</hi> Originals, as one can't be thought to <hi>Copy</hi> from the other: Tho <hi>Pſeudo-Hieronymus</hi> is ſo inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous as to tell us he is beholding to <hi>Seleucus</hi> for this fine Legend; and this gives us ſome hint how this came to be Minted.</p>
            <p>Firſt, we have the Letter of <hi>Chromatius</hi> and <hi>Heliodorus</hi> to S. <hi>Hierom,</hi> pretending that <hi>Armonius</hi> and <hi>Virinus</hi> had told them that <hi>S. Hierom</hi> had an <hi>Hebrew</hi> Goſpel of <hi>S. Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> wherein the Infancy of the <hi>V. Mary,</hi> and our <hi>Saviour</hi> were written, which they deſire him to turn into <hi>Latin:</hi> To this the Falſe <hi>Hierom</hi> anſwers, excuſing the difficulty of the Work, for that the Apoſtle deſign'd not to have it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, that therefore he had <hi>ſealed it up</hi> in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and not added it to his <hi>Common</hi> Goſpel, to the end it might be <hi>ſecret,</hi> but delivered it to be kept by ſome <hi>choice</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Men, who would not ſuffer it to be Tranſlated, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gave ſome Relations that it contained; till <hi>Seleucus</hi> firſt publiſh'd it, wherein tho he ſpake Truth as to the Hiſtory and Miracles, yet added many Falſhoods as to the Doctrines, and therefore he promiſes to make a verbal and exact Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation from the <hi>Hebrew:</hi> But the Forgery is ſo ill ſpun, and the Blunders ſo groſs, as to give as good a Character of the
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:51732:5"/>Author's Talents, as of his Veracity. The Author probably was <hi>Seleucus</hi> the <hi>Manichaean,</hi> or <hi>Leucius,</hi> as <hi>J. Caſaubon</hi> reads in ſome Manuſcripts, the firſt Syllable being left out; and 'tis for this Reaſon that S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> diſputing againſt <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the <hi>Manichee,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Si illius Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphae Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae ubi <hi>Joa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim,</hi> Pater <hi>Mariae</hi> legitur, detinerer. L. 23.</note> rejects ſuch Apocryphal Writings, perhaps the very ſame: and elſewhere condemns this <hi>Leucius.</hi> But he can be condemn'd by none more ſeverely than by a Pope, <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> who calls him a <hi>Diſciple of the Devil,</hi> and ſays, all his Books are Apocryphal; which reflects a little odly on that other Pope, who not only received this For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, but founded a Day and Office upon the ſhameleſs Fable of this Heretick.</p>
            <p>But becauſe <hi>Pſeudo-Jacobus</hi> writes with greater Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and would intrude his ſtuff for Scripture, it may not be amiſs, or undiverting, to ſee what is ſo Authoritatively deliver'd with the Apoſtolical Benediction at the end. <q>
                  <hi>He begins the Story, telling us of one</hi> Joachim, <hi>who is ſaid to be very Rich and Charitable, and to give double Offerings to God of his Eſtate. Now, we are told, that when the great Feaſt of the Lord drew near, the People of</hi> Iſrael <hi>brought all their Offerings, amongst whom was</hi> Joachim, <hi>none of the leaſt eminent; and</hi> Reuben <hi>ſtood up againſt him, and ſaid, It is not lawful for you to offer yours, becauſe you have not made Seed in</hi> Iſrael. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which the Gentleman was very ſad, and went to the Genealogy of the Twelve Tribes, ſaying to himſelf, I'l ſee whether in the Tribes of</hi> Iſrael <hi>I can find any who are</hi> without <hi>Seed. Having accordingly made an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, he ſees that all the</hi> Righteous <hi>had</hi> Seed: <hi>Thence he calls</hi> Abraham <hi>to mind, and how God was pleaſed to give him</hi> Iſaac <hi>in his old Age.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> Joachim <hi>was much caſt down, and appear'd not to his Wife, but retir'd into the Wilderneſs, where he fixed his Tent, and faſted fourty days, and fourty nights, ſaying with himſelf, I will not go up to eat or drink, but my Prayer ſhall be my Food.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="viii" facs="tcp:51732:6"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>But in the mean while his Wife</hi> Ann <hi>endured two griefs, her Widowhood and her Barrenneſs. Now the great Feſtival came, and</hi> Judith <hi>her Maid ſaid to her, How long will you afflict your ſpirit? It's not lawful for you to mourn, for 'tis a great Holy-day: Come, Madam, put on your beſt Dreſs. But</hi> Ann <hi>anſwer'd, Depart from me, I will not do it: God has grievouſly humbled me.</hi> Judith <hi>on the other ſide was ſtill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate with her Miſtreſs, and ſaid, What ſhall I ſay to you if you will not hear? Deſervedly has God ſhut up your Womb. And</hi> Ann <hi>was greatly troubled at it, and was prevail'd upon to put off her Mourning habit, and to put on her Wedding garments: And about the Ninth hour ſhe went into the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to walk, where ſeeing a</hi> Laurel-Tree, <hi>ſhe ſits down under it, and pours forth her Prayers to this effect; God of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers bleſs me, and hear my Prayer, as thou bleſſed'ſt the Womb of</hi> Sarah, <hi>and gaveſt her a Son.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When looking up into Heaven ſhe ſaw a Sparrows Neſt, which made her lament after a very grievous rate, and burſt into ſuch expeſſions; Wo is me! To what can I be likened? or, What Womb brought me forth, that I ſhould be a Curſe before the Children of</hi> Iſrael? <hi>For they laugh at, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach me, they throw me out of the Temple of the Lord my God. Alas! what am I like to? I can't be compar'd to the Birds of the Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And after this manner ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, alledging to God, that he deals worſe by her than by any other ſort of Creatures, worſe than by the</hi> Birds <hi>and</hi> Beaſts, <hi>nay, than by the</hi> Elements, <hi>for that all theſe are</hi> fruitful. <hi>And no ſooner had ſhe finiſh'd her Complaint, but the Angel of the Lord took</hi> his flight <hi>towards her, and ſaid to her,</hi> Ann, Ann, <hi>the Lord has heard thy Prayer, thou ſhalt conceive, and bring forth a Child, and thy name ſhall be ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated over all the World. Then</hi> Ann <hi>very gratefully makes a Vow to God, to make a Preſent to him of the Child which ſhe ſhall have, whether Male or Female, to Miniſter to him all the days of its life.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="ix" facs="tcp:51732:6"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>And after this, behold two Angels came, and ſaid to her,</hi> Joachim <hi>your Husband is coming with his Flocks: For the Angel of the Lord came down to him, and ſaid</hi> Joachim, Joachim, <hi>God has heard thy Prayer, go hence, behold,</hi> Ann <hi>thy Wife ſhall conceive in her Womb. And he went down, and call'd his Shepherds, ſaying, Bring me ten pure Ewe Lambs, and they ſhall be for my</hi> God; <hi>Twelve Calves which ſhall be for the</hi> Prieſts; <hi>and an Hundred Goats for the</hi> People.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> Joachim <hi>came with his Flocks, and</hi> Ann <hi>ſtood in the Gate and ſaw him coming, and ran and hung on his neck, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, now ſhe knew ſhe was Bleſſed, and ſo ſings her</hi> Magnificat.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> Joachim <hi>reſted the firſt day in his Houſe, and on the morrow made his offerings; but being more incredulous than his Wife, he deſires a</hi> Sign <hi>for the confirmation of what the Angel had foretold, which accordingly appears on the</hi> Ephod. <hi>To conclude,</hi> Ann <hi>at the end of nine months is delivered of the Virgin</hi> Mary. <hi>And the</hi> Birth <hi>is little leſs Miraculous than the</hi> Conception.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Afterwards, when ſhe was ſix Months old, her Mother put her on the ground, to try whether ſhe could walk upright; and ſhe walked ſeven steps, and came into her Mothers Lap. And</hi> Ann <hi>ſaid, As the Lord lives, thou ſhalt not walk on the Earth, till I ſhall have offer'd thee in the Lord's Temple. And ſhe made a Chappel in her Chamber, and whatever was impure or common, was for her ſake remov'd: And ſhe had</hi> Holy Hebrew Maids <hi>to wait on her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt year being over,</hi> Joachim <hi>made a great Feaſt, and invited the</hi> High Prieſts <hi>and</hi> Scribes, <hi>with the</hi> Sanhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drin <hi>and all the</hi> People; <hi>and he offer'd up his Oblations to the Prieſts, and they bleſſed him, ſaying, God of our Fathers bleſs this Girl, and give her a famous and eternal Name in all Generations. And all the People ſaid,</hi> Amen, Amen. <hi>Then they offer'd her to the Prieſts, and they bleſſed her, ſaying, The moſt high God bleſs this Child, and bleſs her with a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that ſhall have no end. Then the Mother ſnatching her
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:51732:7"/>away, gave her the Teat, and withal made this Song; I will ſing Praiſes to the Lord my God, who has viſited me, and taken from me the Reproach of mine Enemies. The Lord God has given the manifold Fruit of Righteouſneſs in his ſight; who ſhall declare to the Sons of</hi> Reuben <hi>that</hi> Ann <hi>gives ſuck?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Singing this, ſhe carried her into her Chappel, and went forth and Miniſtred to them. The Feaſt being over, they went away rejoycing, and gave her the name of</hi> Mary, <hi>glorifying the God of</hi> Iſrael.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When ſhe was two years old,</hi> Joachim <hi>would have carried her to the Temple to pay their Vow, but that</hi> Ann <hi>hindred it till the completion of the third year, which was then done with a great deal of ſolemnity. The</hi> Hebrew <hi>holy</hi> Maids <hi>being invited, took each their Lamps and lighted them, and went without looking back till they came to the Temple; where the High Prieſt receiv'd and kiſt her, and ſaid,</hi> Mary, <hi>the Lord has magnified thy Name in all Generations; and more to that effect. And he placed her upon the third step of the Altar, and the Lord God ſent his Grace upon her, and ſhe Danced, and all the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>fell in love with her. But the wonder is, ſhe took no notice of her Parents, and they went home admiring and praiſing God that ſhe turn'd not after them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>After this we are told, how ſhe was educated here like a Dove, and fed by the hands of an Angel; till being twelve years of Age, a great Council was held how to diſpoſe of her. This was open'd by the High Prieſt, who tells the reſt of the Prieſts her Age, and asks their advice, leſt the Sanctuary forſooth be</hi> defiled. <hi>The Anſwer was, Do thou ſtand at the Altar and pray for her, and whatſoever God ſhall manifeſt to thee, that will we do. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this the H. Prieſt, in his</hi> Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical <hi>Habit, goes into the Holy of Holies and makes ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for her, when behold the Angel of the Lord ſtood by him, and ſaid to him,</hi> Zachary, Zachary, <hi>go forth, and call together the Widowers of the People, and let all bring their Rods; and to whom God ſhall ſhow the Sign, his Wife ſhall ſhe be to keep.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="xi" facs="tcp:51732:7"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now the Heralds went over all the Land of</hi> Judea, <hi>and the Trumpet of the Lord ſounded, and all ran forth; and</hi> Joſeph <hi>throwing away his Ax, went out to meet them: So they went all together to the H. Prieſt, who taking the Rods they brought, from them, went into the Temple and pray'd; after Prayer he took the Rods and went forth, and reſtor'd to every one his Rod, and no ſign appear'd. But</hi> Joſeph <hi>took his the laſt, and a</hi> Dove <hi>immediately flew out of it, to the no ſmall amazement of the ſpectators, and lighted on</hi> Joſeph<hi>'s head. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this the Prieſt ſaid to him, The Lord has choſen you to take this Virgin to keep her. Which</hi> Joſeph <hi>oppoſes, making anſwer, I have Children, and am old, whereas ſhe is a young Girl; whence I am afraid of becoming ridiculous to the Children of</hi> Iſrael. <hi>At laſt the Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance being propos'd to him, which God executed on</hi> Corah, Dathan <hi>and</hi> Abiram, <hi>being put by it into a dreadful fright, he makes no longer reſiſtance, but ſays,</hi> Mary, <hi>I take thee from the Temple of the Lord, but I will leave thee at home, and go about my Carpenters Trade: And I pray God to keep thee all the days of thy life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then we are told how, not long after this, the Prieſts had a Council about making a Veil to the Temple, for which the</hi> Holy Maids <hi>of the Houſe of</hi> David <hi>were call'd, and all took their work by Lot,</hi> true Purple <hi>falling to</hi> Mary's <hi>ſhare. About which time</hi> Zacharias <hi>dying, is ſucceeded by</hi> Samuel. Mary <hi>having receiv'd her</hi> Purple, <hi>went to work; and taking a Pitcher, went to draw water, and ſhe heard a Voice,</hi> Hail Mary full of Grace: <hi>and ſhe look'd about on both ſides to know whence the Voice came, but could ſee nothing. She comes trembling into the Houſe, puts down her Pitcher, and taking the Purple, ſat down in her ſeat to work; and the Angel of the Lord ſtood before her, and ſaid,</hi> Fear not <hi>Mary,</hi> for thou, <hi>&amp;c. Then are intermixt ſome Paſſages taken out of the</hi> Evangeliſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>After which it's ſaid, that ſhe being ſix months gone, and ſixteen years old,</hi> Joſeph <hi>return'd from his buſineſs, about which he had been ſome years without coming home to his
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:51732:8"/>Wife. Now finding her big, he was much ſtartled, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulated with her in many words; but is at laſt advertis'd of the whole matter by an Angel. But the pity was, that a Scribe coming to ſpeak with</hi> Joſeph, <hi>perceives</hi> Mary <hi>great with Child, and upon this makes a terrible outcry. Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately Juſtice lays hold on</hi> Joſeph, <hi>and he is brought before the H. Prieſt; and being both examin'd, he maintains that he had not kept company with her; and ſhe ſays, with a great deal of bitter crying, that ſhe had neither</hi> his <hi>nor any</hi> other <hi>Mans. They both denying, the Prieſt makes them drink the Water of Redargution, which having done them no hurt, to the great aſtoniſhment of the beholders, the Prieſt ſaid, that ſince God had not manifeſted their ſin, neither did</hi> he <hi>condemn them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then is inſerred what is related by St.</hi> Luke, <hi>how upon the Edict of</hi> Auguſtus, Joſeph <hi>leads her to</hi> Bethlehem. <hi>But this is not without enriching the Relation, and uſing even</hi> wicked <hi>and</hi> immodeſt <hi>expreſſions. At laſt we are told, how ſhe was Deliver'd in a</hi> Cave, <hi>ſaving S.</hi> Luke's <hi>Honour,</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph <hi>having found her a Midwife by a great Miracle, and in his journey met with plenty of great Miracles: which Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife tells another who is call'd</hi> Salome; <hi>who not believing that a</hi> Virgin <hi>had brought forth a Child, comes to make the proof; which is ſo profanely and impudently deſcribed, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with other matters of as vile a nature as can well be imagined. All which declare it to be made in deriſion of</hi> Chriſtianity; <hi>but that the better to make the Cheat paſs, there are inſerted in form of Rapſody, ſome</hi> Expreſſions <hi>of the</hi> Evangeliſts, <hi>and ſome</hi> Rites <hi>to which colour may be given by ſome paſſages of the</hi> Old Teſtament, <hi>beſides the</hi> ſimplicity <hi>of the manner of Speech, and ſeveral</hi> Hebraiſms <hi>affected. By the help of which he thought he</hi> might, <hi>as he</hi> doth <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, I</hi> James <hi>writ this Hiſtory in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>where a tumult being rais'd, I withdrew my ſelf into a deſert place, till the death of</hi> Herod; <hi>and then like an</hi> Apoſtle <hi>he gives the</hi> Bleſſing.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:51732:8"/>
            <p>The firſt Man that produced this rich Goſpel, and Tranſlated it from the <hi>Greek</hi> was
<note n="*" place="margin">Prot-evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion cum E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelica Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoria S. <hi>Mari</hi> Evangeliſtae, &amp; vita ejus in 8. <hi>Baſil.</hi> 1552.</note> 
               <hi>Poſtel;</hi> and it came out with the Notes of <hi>Bibliander,</hi> after which it appear'd with a great deal of ſuitable company, under the Title of
<note n="†" place="margin">Orthodoxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapha. Gr. Lat Editore Gry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeo. <hi>Bald.</hi> 1569.</note> 
               <hi>Orthodox Writings,</hi> which have as much right all of them to this Title, as <hi>this</hi> Goſpel has to the <hi>Brother of our Lord.</hi> This Book indeed is ſo agreable to the <hi>Genius</hi> of the firſt Publiſher, as to make
<note n="‖" place="margin">L' Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction au Traitè de la conformité des Merveilles An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciennes avec les Modernes. ch. 33.</note> 
               <hi>H. Stevens</hi> ſuſpect him to have a finger in the Forgery. But without defrauding him of the praiſes of handing it forth into the World, we may rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonably allow it elder, and probably the <hi>Original,</hi> as hath been ſaid, of the Fable: which is too believ'd by <hi>Caſaubon.</hi> This much is certain, that the <hi>Goſpel</hi> going under the name of S. <hi>James,</hi> the Brother of our Lord, is expreſly nam'd, and condemn'd as <hi>Apocryphal</hi> by
<note n="∴" place="margin">An. 494. Con. Binii. To. 2. p. 264.</note> the <hi>Roman</hi> Synod under <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> about the latter end of the fifth Century, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Book of the <hi>Nativity of our Saviour, and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Mary <hi>and the Midwife;</hi> with all thoſe written by <hi>Leu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius.</hi> We have by the ſame Synod, conſiſting of Seventy Biſhops, condemn'd the ſeveral Goſpels paſſing under the names of <hi>Thaddeus, Matthias, Peter, Barnaby, Thomas, Bartholomew, Andrew,</hi> which no doubt but were fill'd with ſuch like Stories. It is no wonder then, if in the darker Ages ſuch Traſh came to be receiv'd, when it was very hard to make things <hi>incredible</hi> enough to gain <hi>belief;</hi> and no Superſtition ſo groſs as might not paſs under thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Names. We have not only the Book <hi>of the Infancy of Jeſus,</hi> and that <hi>of the Birth of</hi> Mary referr'd to by the Legendaries; but ſome alſo were not aſham'd to own the <hi>Goſpel of S.</hi> Ann. An Inſtance whereof is given in one <hi>Bonaventure</hi> of <hi>Ipres</hi> in <hi>Flanders</hi> by <hi>H. Stevens,</hi> telling us, That <q>
                  <hi>When</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>was grown big enough to work,</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph <hi>began to employ him in his Trade, and once above the reſt having commanded him to Saw a piece of Wood, he ſaw'd it without taking heed to the mark that</hi> Joſeph <hi>had made, ſo
<pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:51732:9"/>that it was too ſhort; at which</hi> Joſeph, <hi>being very angry, threatn'd to beat him, and would have done ſo, had not he made it longer, by taking himſelf one end, and making</hi> Joſeph <hi>take the other, and each one pulling.</hi>
               </q> If ſuch things as theſe are not a ſcandal to Chriſtianity, and the Invention of the Father of Lies, I know not what is.</p>
            <p>But, God be praiſed, it has fell out very happily, that theſe <hi>Falſe Evangeliſts</hi> have notoriouſly given themſelves the Lye; having not either Learning or Wit enough to lay the <hi>Plan</hi> of their Story ſo, as not to claſh with the greateſt Evidences of <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Place.</hi> Hence they bring upon the Stage ſuch perſons as <hi>Iſſachar, Reuben,</hi> &amp;c. who we are certain <hi>never were.</hi> And who, that is in the leaſt acquainted with the Cuſtoms of the <hi>Jews,</hi> can believe, that a Girl of Three years old was ever put into the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> and there liv'd alone, without any body to take care of her, for many years? Certainly if <hi>only</hi> the High Prieſt entred there, and he not above <hi>one</hi> day in the year, and then nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not above <hi>once</hi> or <hi>twice;</hi> and if he entred three or four times, was to be put to death: nothing can be groſſer than to place there a young helpleſs Child. And if we believe this, it is not much if we believe ſhe lived there without Meat, Drink, Bed and Converſation for Ten or a Dozen years. Beſides, that there were no <hi>Nuns</hi> or <hi>Holy Women</hi> in the Temple, as the Story ſuppoſes, is at large proved againſt <hi>Baronius</hi> by
<note n="*" place="margin">Exercit. ad Bar. App. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. N. 21, 22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>Caſaubon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having ſaid ſo much of the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Foundation,</hi> I have but little to add of the following Book <hi>it ſelf.</hi> The Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſher tells you, That <hi>it relates directly to the Glory of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Creator of all things:</hi> And the Approvers tell you, that <hi>they find nothing in it but what is conformable to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical</hi> Roman <hi>Church;</hi> and that <hi>it is very uſeful to maintain the Devotion to S.</hi> Ann. But how directly that Devotion relates to the Glory of the Supream Creator, they may be better able to reconcile than I am. I might eaſily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:51732:9"/>ſome of the Doctrines with thoſe of a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Doctor lately condemn'd at <hi>Rome;</hi> nay, and parallel ſome of the <hi>very Expreſſions,</hi> to ſhew that what is <hi>Heretical</hi> at one time, may be <hi>Orthodox</hi> at another. I might alſo ſhew how the <hi>Legend</hi> came to be patch'd up out of the Hiſtory of <hi>Hannah, Samuel</hi>'s Mother, and that of our ever Bleſſed Lord; and might give a view of ſome other
<note n="†" place="margin">Ave Maria Gratia plena, &amp;c.— &amp; benedicta ſit Anna Mater ſua, de qua ſine macula tua proceſſit caro Virginea.</note> Devotions made to St. <hi>Ann:</hi> But I am afraid I have too extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly already tired the Reader's patience, and therefore do conclude.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51732:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51732:10"/>
            <head>TO THE Queen Regent.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is Divine <hi>Providence,</hi> and not <hi>Fortune</hi> or Humane <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry,</hi> that beſtows Scepters and Crowns; and all <hi>France</hi> viſibly diſcovers in the Regency of YOUR MAJESTY, the Mild and Loving thoughts of the <hi>Divine Regent</hi> of the World, in giving us the Beſt, as well as the Greateſt Princeſs of the Earth to Govern it.</p>
            <p>But may YOUR MAJESTY be pleas'd to ſuffer us, the poor <hi>Daughters</hi> of St. <hi>JOSEPH,</hi> to declare, That it is in You that we have not only <hi>obſerv'd,</hi> but <hi>felt</hi> one of the moſt beautiful <hi>draughts</hi> of this Divine <hi>Providence;</hi> which is, That as it hath its <hi>Eye</hi> and <hi>Scepter</hi> over the leaſt of the <hi>Worms</hi> that creep upon the Earth, as well as over the moſt exalted of <hi>Monarchs</hi> who is lifted up on the Throne; So, <hi>Great Queen,</hi> Your <hi>Regency</hi> bearing its Glory already beyond Admiration, by ſo many Glorious Actions which ſeem to rob each other of their ſplendor in the Government of Your State, You judged that it would have loſt ſomewhat of its Luſtre, had not You ſhew'd Your ſelf as well a Charitable <hi>Mother</hi> of the poor <hi>Orphans,</hi> as a worthy <hi>Queen Regent</hi> of this great <hi>Monarchy.</hi> You have ſaid from the beginning, what the <hi>Wiſdom Incarnate</hi> ſaid formerly, in this World, <hi>Suffer theſe little Souls to come to me.</hi> I am pleas'd to aſſiſt the Deſigns of <hi>Preventing Grace,</hi> which has drawn 'em out of the evil ſteps and perils of great Miſeries, to which an
<pb facs="tcp:51732:11"/>extreme Poverty would have reduc'd 'em: Divine <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> has taken 'em into its care, and it pleaſes Me to make My ſelf its Agent, or Lieutenant, in the means of Loving and Helping them; I receive them under my Protection, and into My Boſom.</p>
            <p>Truly it is an Action ſo much the more Powerful and Meritorious before God, as it has the leſs of Intereſt, and as he alone could be its <hi>motive:</hi> But 'tis an Action which perfectly reſembles, and worthily honours the ſteps of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence, of whoſe Favours and Succours, the Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as well as the Great, the <hi>Shorn</hi> as well as the <hi>Crowned</hi> heads partake.</p>
            <p>The moſt ſublime cares in which YOUR MAJESTY is conſtantly to Admiration taken up for the Glory and Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this State, are, it muſt be confeſs'd, the lively <hi>Colours</hi> of its <hi>Pourtraiture:</hi> But Divine <hi>Providence</hi> was willing that the little deſtitute Maids, whoſe Honour and Life You pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, ſhould give the <hi>Shades.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That therefore all <hi>France</hi> may admire the wonders of Your Conduct, Your poor <hi>Maids</hi> of St. <hi>Joſeph</hi> will do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe in the World but publiſh to it the Miracles of Your Charity, and declare in the condition wherein we mean Creatures are, That as there is nothing too <hi>high</hi> for Your <hi>Regency,</hi> ſo nothing is too <hi>low</hi> for Your <hi>Goodneſs;</hi> which by too much meriting towards us, puts us into an entire ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of being ever able to be ſufficiently Thankful.</p>
            <p>Behold, nevertheleſs, a ſmall Teſtimony of our profound Acknowledgment, which carries our Hearts to the Feet of Your Majeſty by this little Work and <hi>Abridgment of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives of St.</hi> Ann, which we adjudged ought to be, if not worthy, at leaſt not unworthy of Your Eyes, for the dignity of the Subject which it treats. And the motives which invited us to this Duty are, That as it was the day of St. <hi>Ann,</hi> when God inſpir'd into us the firſt deſigns of Erecting an <hi>Houſe</hi> after the Pattern of <hi>his,</hi> where Maids
<pb facs="tcp:51732:11"/>ſhould be bred and inſtructed till the time they be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for, in like manner as the Holy Virgin her Daughter was ſo carefully and ſo holily educated by her: So is it this ſame Saint which we believe to have been among the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Cauſes, that which procur'd us from the Firſt this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable favour of the greateſt Queen in the World, who imitates her <hi>Virtues,</hi> as well as worthily bears her <hi>Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore after having taken St. <hi>Ann</hi> for our <hi>Tutelar,</hi> and the <hi>Governant</hi> in this <hi>Houſe,</hi> and Dedicated to her a Chappel in the Deſign of erecting thereto a <hi>Confrairy</hi> in her Honour, who hath tied us to <hi>her ſelf</hi> by <hi>Adoption,</hi> and by <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> to <hi>Jeſus</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> who compoſe her Family; we have preſum'd for the beſt return of Thanks which we have been able to preſent to Your Majeſty, to repreſent to You upon this little Paper, as in a Map, a World of Merits and Perfections which were in this Great Saint, ſo to make yours acknowledg'd and admir'd, and God prais'd by ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>your Majeſties</hi> Life a true Image and Abſtract of <hi>Hers.</hi> For if St. <hi>Ann</hi> were of the Blood-Royal of <hi>David,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of the Race of Patriarchs and Prophets, and ſo much honour'd by God; all the World knows that Your Majeſty is of a Royal Birth, ſo exalted, as the Sun always honours it with its Light, having no Horizon or ſetting for its Realms.</p>
            <p>If St. <hi>Ann</hi> were Great in <hi>Piety</hi> and Devotion; and if imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating the ancient <hi>Ann, Samuel</hi>'s Mother, ſhe had frequent recourſe to the Sanctuary by her Prayers and Vows; the <hi>Piety</hi> which Your Majeſty has from Your Anceſtors, <hi>Charles</hi> 5. and <hi>Philip</hi> 2. is ſo <hi>familiar</hi> to You, as it may be call'd the <hi>Star</hi> which commands Your Inclinations; the <hi>Spirit</hi> which gives Life to Your Actions, and <hi>Succeſs</hi> to all Your Deſigns.</p>
            <p>If St. <hi>Ann</hi> be worthily nam'd by St. <hi>Damaſcene</hi> a <hi>Reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Turtle,</hi> foraſmuch as ſhe paſt good part of her Life in ſolitude and ſighing; alas, <hi>Madam,</hi> how many years has
<pb facs="tcp:51732:12"/>
               <hi>your Majeſty</hi> led a Life more like to a <hi>ſolitary</hi> Perſon, than to the <hi>chiefeſt</hi> and the moſt <hi>virtuous</hi> Queen of the Univerſe!</p>
            <p>If St. <hi>Ann</hi> were great in the Love which ſhe bore to her <hi>God,</hi> whom ſhe could ſcarce ever ſuffer to be out of her ſight; and to her <hi>Neighbor,</hi> by the aſſiſtance ſhe gave to all who were any ways neceſſitous; alas, Great Queen, it is at Your <hi>expence,</hi> and by Your own <hi>experience,</hi> that You have learnt, like the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> both to ſuffer <hi>for</hi> God, and to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>with</hi> the Miſerable. And a time was when the Divine Providence had taken away the uſe and diſpoſal of Riches, thereby to augment Your Charity towards <hi>God,</hi> but which at this day has given You the means whereby You may exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe Charity towards Your <hi>Subjects</hi> with a Liberality as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſive as exceeds both hopes and deſires.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> made St. <hi>Ann</hi> bear the Fruit of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction,</hi> and the firſt fruits of our <hi>Redemption;</hi> our Sacred Monarch, who ſhall, if it pleaſe God, one day place the <hi>Flowerdeluces</hi> above the Creſcent, and the other fair flower of Your Majeſties Crown, are the Fruits as well of Your <hi>Prayers,</hi> and of Your Royal <hi>Virtues,</hi> as of your <hi>Womb.</hi> Have not ſo many reiterated Vows, ſo many ſighs of <hi>your Majeſty</hi> ſent toward Heaven, made you the peaceable Dove of this State, and the Calm of our Storms?</p>
            <p>If St. <hi>Ann</hi> gave Leſſons to her little Daughter, the holy Virgin, of living in Humility, Charity and Holineſs; how many Bleſſings owe we to Heaven, to ſee this Royal Spirit with which Your Majeſty was born, and ſo many excellent Virtues and Royal Qualities ſlide ſo admirably into the Eyes, Ears, and Spirit of our good young King? How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo good a Government ſhall we not have a King of Wonders, one Liberal, Generous, and Pious?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, If <hi>Jeſus</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> were <hi>both</hi> the moſt excellent Maſterpieces of the Divine Power, <hi>both</hi> the Richeſt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Divine Wiſdom, <hi>both</hi> the Divineſt Objects of its Goodneſs, <hi>both</hi> the Worthieſt Subjects of the Cares and the
<pb facs="tcp:51732:12"/>Government of St. <hi>Ann,</hi> yet hinder'd her not from dayly <hi>adopting</hi> and aſſociating to theſe two noble parts of her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, ſeveral confiding Souls; So, tho the Attention of Your Majeſty more peculiarly regards the Education of the <hi>King,</hi> and the ſecond Hope of <hi>France,</hi> his Brother; <hi>both</hi> given by Heaven for the Reſt of this Monarchy, and for the Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Your Majeſty; yet You diſdain not to open Your Boſom, and to tender the Arms of Your Mercy and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection to the poor little <hi>Orphans,</hi> the <hi>Maids of St.</hi> Joſeph.</p>
            <p>Behold, <hi>MADAM,</hi> the juſt reſemblances of Your Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pattern, which have given us the Confidence of laying at Your <hi>Majeſties</hi> Feet an Abridgment of the Wonders of this Holy Lady, whom God choſe from all Eternity to be the Principle of his Ways in the Salvation of Men; think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we could not better clear our ſelves of the Ingratitude which Your Majeſties Luſtre and exceſs of Goodneſs have made neceſſary, than by a little Treatiſe that contains the <hi>Prerogatives of St.</hi> Ann, to whom <hi>your Majeſty</hi> gives and conſecrates dayly Your <hi>Perſon,</hi> Your <hi>Family,</hi> Your <hi>Realm</hi> and Your <hi>Subjects;</hi> and in conſideration of whom, we bring to the Feet of <hi>your Majeſty</hi> the Vows which we make of living and dying,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R MAJESTIES Moſt Humble, and moſt Obedient, and moſt Obliged Servants, THE MAIDS OF S.</hi> JOSEPH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:51732:13"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle of the <hi>French</hi> Publiſher, to the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>It is about a year ſince, a little Book, intituled,</hi> The Acts of Invocation of St. <hi>Joſeph, compoſed by the R. P.</hi> Chiflet <hi>of the Society of</hi> Jeſus, <hi>accidentally falling into my hands, I Publiſh'd it, and took the boldneſs to Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it to the</hi> Queen. <hi>Now in as much as I could not have the Honour of preſenting it my ſelf, a Great Lady of the Court did me the favour to ſupply this defect, and to preſent it in my name. But it being but a week ſince I receiv'd the Copy of another Treatiſe, Intitul'd,</hi> The Prerogatives of St. <hi>Ann, Dedicated in like manner to her</hi> Majeſty <hi>by the</hi> Maids of St. <hi>Joſeph, it ſeem'd proper to me to Print this as a continuance of the former. I therefore put it to the Preſs as ſoon as I could, not to retard the Fruit that the Publick might thence reap; and, having otherwiſe propos'd to my ſelf, that in things which reſpect the Love of God, together with Chriſtian Piety as well towards St.</hi> Joſeph <hi>as St.</hi> Ann, <hi>as likewiſe the ſervice of our Great Queen, I ought to uſe Diligence, and to give in the time prefixt, as I have endeavoured to do, this little Work; ſo if by Praecipitation of the Impreſſion there be any faults crept in, I beſeech you, Reader, that you would excuſe them, upon the aſſurance I give you, that in the new Edition which I purpoſe ſuddenly to make, I will endeavour to give you content, and to make this Book as Correct as it ſhall be poſſible for me. Receive it therefore, Reader, for a Teſtimony of mine Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, or rather for the Love of your ſelf, which I am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured will not fail of being agreeable, ſeeing it relates</hi> directly <hi>to the Glory of the Supreme Creator of all things.</hi> Farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51732:13"/>
            <head>THE PREROGATIVES OF S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. ANNE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Silence of the Evangeliſts concerning the Merits of St.</hi> Ann.</head>
               <p>IT is Natures beſt <hi>Order</hi> to <hi>conceal</hi> from our eyes what her excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenteſt and chiefeſt Works contain of the utmoſt perfection and greatneſs, as if in this ſhe meant to reproach the Vanity of our minds, which can hardly conceive a good deſire in the <hi>heart,</hi> without bringing it up immediately to the <hi>mouth,</hi> and <hi>publiſhing</hi> it to the Rays of the Sun. Whereas <hi>Heaven,</hi> the moſt wonderful part of the viſible Creation, ſhews not its powerful <hi>influences</hi> which govern all inferior things; or the <hi>Fire,</hi> that imperious <hi>quality</hi> which ſoftens the moſt intractable Metals; or the <hi>Earth</hi> its <hi>Gold,</hi> which it forms within its entrails; or the <hi>Sea</hi> its <hi>Treaſures,</hi> which it incloſes within its Abyſſes.</p>
               <p>An Order that might be ſtil'd Religious, if Nature guided it with Judgment: but is yet better obſerv'd in Grace, which is pleas'd to <hi>cover</hi> and <hi>drown</hi> in Ignorance and Silence the greateſt perfections of the moſt holy and moſt elevated Souls, with the deſign, that being afterward <hi>reveal'd,</hi> they may more attract our admirations and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. And when I conſider how God ſhewed not himſelf to <hi>Moſes,</hi> but in the <hi>tranſient glimps</hi> of a burning buſh, and how he ſays that his habitations are in <hi>darkneſs,</hi> and his thrones in the <hi>clouds,</hi> and that he never abaſes himſelf ſo low as to make our <hi>ſenſes</hi> or our <hi>reaſon</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51732:14"/>of his <hi>ſight,</hi> or of the <hi>knowledg</hi> of his perfections; I diſcover preſently, in my Opinion, the reaſon for which certain Souls, the moſt eminent in ſanctity, and the moſt approaching to the Deity, are a Treaſure <hi>as ineffable as God,</hi> who conceals it from human eyes. The <hi>Athenians</hi> offer'd more Incenſe to that God they <hi>knew not,</hi> than to thoſe who were faſtned to their Shrines, or incloſed in their Temples: So we owe more reverence and honour to thoſe <hi>heroical</hi> and <hi>glorious</hi> Souls who are happily hidden to the World, and <hi>loſt in God,</hi> to be known by him alone, than to thoſe whoſe Virtue has been Preach'd, and who have had an <hi>immortal</hi> glory among Mortals. Theſe have had their <hi>ſhare</hi> in the rewards of the World; thoſe have been <hi>deſpiſed;</hi> Theſe have united the honours of the <hi>Earth</hi> with the merit of thoſe of <hi>Heaven;</hi> thoſe have renounc'd their <hi>own</hi> Glory to procure that of <hi>God.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> having ſaid, that there are certain Souls who are willing to go beyond the firſt Leſſons, who learn by the obſervance of <hi>God</hi>'s Commandments, and the <hi>Churches</hi> Laws, to ſtudy the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted maxims of Chriſtianity, and ſurpaſs the obligations common to all Chriſtians, even ſo far as to the renouncing, hating, and <hi>annihila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> themſelves, to be ſacrific'd on every trial and occaſion to the Empire of Divine Love, which <hi>transforms</hi> them all into God, and makes them <hi>enter into the Powers of the Lord,</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) that is, into an adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Communication,</hi> and as it were into the rights of the ſame Attributes of Purity, Holineſs and Charity of this God, to whoſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> this kind of <hi>Perfect Life</hi> has exalted 'em; this heavenly Doctor call'd ſuch Souls dead, and <hi>hidden in God with Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> becauſe the ſpiritual work of inward <hi>Abnegations,</hi> and <hi>Abandonings</hi> of all their proper <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,</hi> and their own <hi>ſelf</hi> into that of God, falling not under the ſenſe and reaſon of men, it muſt alſo thence be, that men are not capable of the <hi>Perfections</hi> which this Labour acquires them: which makes him ſay, That he eſteems them greater for the <hi>perfections</hi> which they have and diſcover not, than for thoſe which would carry their Reputation and Name over the Univerſe, and acquire 'em the Acclamations and Honours of the World. Words which ſeem to have been read by that Ancient, when he ſaid, That Virtue is hidden within her ſelf, that our eyes were too feeble to ſupport her luſtre; and that ſhe hid for thoſe who were moſt aſſiduous at her Sacrifices, Beauties which would obſcure thoſe of the Sun, if the generality of men were ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of obſerving 'em.</p>
               <p>Hence I draw this advantagious Concluſion for the Honour of St. <hi>Ann,</hi> That had men looked on her perfection with a ſteddy eye, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51732:14"/>a conſtant view, ſhe had not appear'd greater to their eyes than <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> to ours, which tho the <hi>vaſteſt</hi> in extent of all our Planets, the moſt <hi>perfect</hi> too and moſt <hi>beautiful,</hi> ſeems the <hi>ſmalleſt,</hi> becauſe he is the <hi>fartheſt</hi> removed from our ſight. St. <hi>Ann</hi> was a <hi>Myſtery</hi> hidden from Eternity <hi>in God,</hi> who was pleaſed to make uſe of her for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions of his firſt Deſigns, and for giving by her the firſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacks to <hi>death,</hi> which had introduc'd into the World; demonſtrating how, if the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of one Woman had given beginning to its <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts,</hi> the <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Generoſity</hi> of another ſhould beat down its <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies,</hi> and overturn its <hi>Empire;</hi> ſince in the ordinary courſe of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſhe conceiv'd and gave to the World a Daughter, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd neither its Way nor Dominion. If then in this miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble caſe of our race, our Impotence be ſuch, as not to be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the power, and to oppoſe our ſelves to the violence of <hi>Death,</hi> a St. <hi>Ann</hi> be found alone in Nature, who has done that which none could tell how to do, taken from Death the firſt Pretenſions and Rights which it had uſurped over human births; Who can have thoughts capable to form an Idea of her <hi>merit?</hi> or words to expreſs what is not beneath both what ſhe <hi>was,</hi> and what we <hi>owe</hi> to her? Add, how this Saint having ſtudied nothing but continual <hi>Annihila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of her <hi>ſelf,</hi> and <hi>Glorifications</hi> of her <hi>God,</hi> ſhe retain'd nothing of the Earth, but made her ſelf wholly Celeſtial, whoſe merit was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore remov'd from all <hi>human</hi> knowledg, and reſerv'd for the <hi>Divine</hi> alone. And as <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great ſaid, That the Scepter and Crown of the World were not, but for the Virtues of him who admitted nothing worthy to bound his Ambition, but what was not known to the reſt of men, and what the greateſt of the Gods kept <hi>conceal'd</hi> in his brain; She alſo whom <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> had deſign'd for the Regency and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Family, to command there as the Virgins Mother, who was His, required far other qualifications than common Morality, and ought to have far different Virtues from thoſe, which <hi>ordinary</hi> holineſs teaches all men: which therefore have been kept unknown, by reaſon of the <hi>greatneſs</hi> and <hi>exceſs</hi> of this <hi>merit.</hi> But God alone, who is able to give the juſt praiſes of holy Actions to every one according to the weight and excellence of their value, has been pleaſed to draw them out of ſilence in <hi>this</hi> Age, by an Annual <hi>Commemoration</hi> and ſolemn <hi>Feaſt</hi> in his Church, to ſhew them unto all the World in the Glory of their Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs; and has diſcover'd to us two ſorts, ſome External, which ſhe borrows elſewhere; others Internal, with which ſhe adorns her Soul. For</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51732:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The External Perfections of St.</hi> ANN.</head>
               <p>I Advance them from the conſideration of her Daughter; for if the goodneſs of the Fruit neceſſarily proves that of the Tree, this fair Plant of Eternity, St. <hi>Ann,</hi> can't be better known than by her Daughter the <hi>Holy Virgin;</hi> and tho one ſhould write in her honour as many Volumes as are in the World, there could not hence be given us ſo perfect a knowledg of her <hi>Prerogatives,</hi> as is in ſimply ſaying, that ſhe was the <hi>Mother</hi> of the <hi>Mother of God,</hi> and the <hi>Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother of God</hi> himſelf.</p>
               <p>It is this Tree that the Angels ſhewed to St. <hi>Bridgid,</hi> ſaying to her, Figure to your ſelf, chaſt Spouſe of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> a Royal Eagle, who going to make her Neſt, and prepare a Lodging for her young Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, goes from Foreſt to Foreſt, flies from Mountain to Mountain, to chuſe a Tree which may ſerve her deſign, and having met with that wich ſurpaſſes all others in heighth and beauty, which has the deepeſt and ſtrongeſt Roots, and the beſt defended from Storms and Tempeſts, ſhe ſtops there, and makes choice of the ſtrongeſt Branch, and the neareſt to Heaven, to feed there, and breed her young ones.</p>
               <p>Imagine now that God is this Eagle, who running over with his Eyes, as it were, ſo many beautiful Trees, all the Women who were to be from the firſt to the laſt, perceiv'd not any one ſo worthy to receive the Glorious Virgin, who was to be the <hi>little Neſt</hi> of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Eaglet,</hi> who is the Word Incarnate, as St. <hi>Ann,</hi> in whom he reſted himſelf, as in the Tree of <hi>Paradice,</hi> which he knew to be the <hi>talleſt</hi> in Devotion, the <hi>deepeſt</hi> in Humility, the <hi>largeſt</hi> in Charity, and of the moſt <hi>pleaſant odour</hi> in Sanctity.</p>
               <p>O <hi>Beautiful Tree!</hi> and far other than that which was repreſented in a Picture at the triumphant entry of <hi>Mary de Medicis,</hi> Queen Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Lewis</hi> 13. which bore <hi>Scepters</hi> for <hi>Boughs, Crowns</hi> for <hi>Flowers, Kings</hi> for the <hi>Stock,</hi> and little <hi>Deities</hi> for the <hi>Fruits.</hi> St. <hi>Ann</hi> was the fair <hi>Tree</hi> of the Genealogy of <hi>Jeſus</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> whoſe <hi>Stock</hi> is made up with the <hi>Davids,</hi> the <hi>Solomons,</hi> and other Kings whoſe <hi>Flowers</hi> are <hi>Diadems;</hi> but the Holy <hi>Virgin,</hi> the richeſt <hi>Crown,</hi> as being the fineſt <hi>Flower</hi> of Heaven and Earth, and her <hi>Fruit</hi> is the Incarnate <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Certainly as the moſt glorious Diadem of the Firſt of the uncreated Perſons, is the Production of his <hi>Word</hi> the ſecond Perſon, whom he begat in the ſplendor of Saints; ſo, if, in one word, you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51732:15"/>would know the price of that Crown which St. <hi>Ann</hi> bore both on Earth and in Heaven, it muſt be ſaid, and this is to ſay all, that her Treaſure and her Crown, was the giving <hi>being</hi> to <hi>her</hi> who gave it to a <hi>God,</hi> which is to be Crown'd with the Merits of <hi>Mary,</hi> like the Tree with its Flowers and Fruit.</p>
               <p>Whence it is to be concluded, That the Dignity, the Grace, and the Holineſs of this <hi>only,</hi> and only <hi>Perfect</hi> Daughter, ought to reflect back to her Mother, even to a point, That ſhe render'd her incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable in <hi>Sanctity,</hi> as ſhe was in her <hi>Dignity.</hi> For of two things, one muſt of neceſſity happen, Either that this holy Virgin <hi>had not</hi> the Power, or that <hi>having</hi> the Power, ſhe communicated to her whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we can fancy greateſt in Grace. Her <hi>Paps</hi> have too much credit and acceſs with the <hi>Word,</hi> her Son, not to have the Power, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the terms of <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> the <hi>Pap</hi> of his Heavenly Father, which gave <hi>foecundity</hi> to all Nature, would alſo, as he had been the Principle of the Univerſe, by being <hi>Mamelle de ſon Pere,</hi> the <hi>Virgin</hi> ſhould be <hi>his;</hi> and that from the Boſom of his Mother ſhould proceed a Power, (but yet not without proportion) and a Force to eſtabliſh a World of Grace to <hi>make</hi> Saints, and to <hi>make</hi> them <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> of Glory. So that it is true in ſome ſort, and good Divinity to ſay, That the Felicity of the Saints is deriv'd from <hi>Mary,</hi> and that there is no body who is not oblig'd to her for the <hi>fortification</hi> of his Patience, for the <hi>Victory</hi> over his Temptations, for <hi>Preſervation</hi> from Falls, for <hi>Augmentation</hi> of his Merits, for his final <hi>Grace,</hi> and finally, for his <hi>Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Principle ſuppos'd, who will doubt that St. <hi>Ann</hi> was not the Maſterpriece of <hi>Maries</hi> Workmanſhip, and that the <hi>Power</hi> of this laſt, was not the <hi>Meaſure</hi> of the Excellence of the former? She could make a Prodigy of Virtue, and a Miracle of Greatneſs, therefore ſhe did; and not only from the time that She <hi>was</hi> her Daughter, but ev'n <hi>before</hi> She was created, we may ſay, That She labour'd on this Maſterpiece. And it is one of the greateſt Miracles of the Myſteries of our Religion, that the <hi>Children</hi> give Life to their <hi>Parents;</hi> and thoſe who are not yet, give admirable Advantages to thoſe who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready are.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Adam,</hi> according to Nature, and his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> according to Grace; the <hi>Virgin</hi> is the <hi>Mother</hi> of the <hi>Saviour,</hi> by the ſhadowing of the Holy Spirit, and is likewiſe the eldeſt <hi>Daughter</hi> to the Redeemer. Thus St. <hi>Ann</hi> is in the ſtate of Grace, the <hi>Daughter</hi> of her Daughter, the <hi>Holy Virgin,</hi> by a <hi>Plenitude</hi> of Grace, which She from her received.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51732:16"/>
               <p>Which ought not to be thought ſtrange by him, who has taſted the Senſe, and univerſal Conſent of the Fathers, who aſſert, that what was giv'n in <hi>Plenitude</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ought in <hi>Proportion</hi> to be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the <hi>Holy Virgin;</hi> that they <hi>both</hi> were buſied in the cares of our Salvation with the ſame Courage, tho not the ſame Power: It's then the Spirit of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not only diffus'd in the new, but has its extent over all the <hi>Old Teſtament;</hi> and no Body was ſav'd, but by his Merits <hi>anticipated;</hi> wherefore ſhould one deny <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to have in favour of the <hi>foreſeen</hi> Merits of his Mother, granted ſome Graces as well <hi>before,</hi> as <hi>after</hi> his Conception, to certain Souls, eſpecially to thoſe moſt near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alli'd to him.</p>
               <p>Among theſe, St. <hi>Ann,</hi> in Conſideration of the <hi>Merits</hi> of this Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, was elevated to the <hi>Prerogatives</hi> and <hi>Crowns,</hi> which ought to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the degree of <hi>Alliance</hi> which ſhe had to her, which was no leſs than of a Mother to a Daughter, an <hi>Alliance</hi> which eſtabliſhes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The firſt Reaſon of the Prerogatives of St.</hi> ANN.</head>
               <p>SHE gave to the <hi>Virgin</hi> Being and Life, which is the deareſt Treaſure of Man, and the Foundation of other Perfections. In exchange, therefore, it is reaſonable the <hi>Virgin</hi> ſhould impart to <hi>Her</hi> all the Noble Qualities, which might make a Soul fill'd with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency to her God.</p>
               <p>For if our Lady had an extream Zeal to carry <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> into the Houſe of her Couſin <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſo to ſanctify her Child, while he was inclos'd in her Womb; if this Zeal thought long, and her Love gave her Wings to fly thither without fear of the Inconveniences and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigues of the Journey, with deſign of procuring Holineſs to her <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and her <hi>Blood.</hi> God having put a perfect <hi>Order</hi> in her Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Loves; muſt it not be ſaid, That that which She had for the <hi>reſt</hi> of her Relations, was but a ſpark in reſpect of the cares which She had for her which was her Mother? And muſt it not be believ'd She gave her a better allotment in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his Graces; there being nothing ſo reaſonable as to do all the good She could to her <hi>Parent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Certainly one of the moſt powerful Arguments for convincing a generous Spirit, is the <hi>fitneſs</hi> of the matter; and this <hi>fitneſs</hi> is more prevalent with good Judgments, than the ſtrictneſs of Laws.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:51732:16"/>
               <p>Whence St. <hi>Thomas</hi> ſpeaking of the two higheſt Myſteries, the <hi>Incarnation</hi> of the Word, and the <hi>Reality</hi> of his Body, the adorable Sacrament and Sacrifice of the <hi>Altar,</hi> ſays they ought to be <hi>believ'd,</hi> becauſe it was <hi>fit</hi> that the Son of God for the perfect <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with us, ſhould be alli'd by the <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with our Nature, and be <hi>really</hi> in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> to ſatisfy the Rules of Love, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a continual <hi>Preſence</hi> of the beloved Object. Laſtly, ſaies this Saint, to ſhew that theſe Myſteries have <hi>fitneſs,</hi> is ſufficient to ſhew, that they are ſo in <hi>Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now there is nothing more reaſonable, than to ſay, That the Virgin lov'd her Mother with a generous and noble Love, that is never without Liberalities and Graces; and that ſhe imparted to her the richeſt Preſents of Heav'n, ſince She had 'em in her <hi>Power,</hi> and her <hi>Hands;</hi> and that in doing ſo, She <hi>ſatisfi'd</hi> the moſt juſt Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Nature, and <hi>obey'd</hi> the Holy Laws of her God, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Honour of her Father and Mother. And as there was in this the greateſt <hi>Fitneſs,</hi> we proceed to ſhew, that there was alſo the greateſt</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. JUSTICE. <hi>The ſecond Reaſon of the Prerogatives of St.</hi> ANN.</head>
               <p>GOD's <hi>Juſtice</hi> would not have leſs Satisfaction for the Sins of <hi>Men,</hi> than the Death of a <hi>God.</hi> Now 'tis wonderful in the <hi>Holy Virgin,</hi> that to conform her ſelf to this <hi>Juſtice,</hi> She <hi>forgot</hi> (if I may ſo ſay) how She was the <hi>Mother of God;</hi> and She <hi>offer'd</hi> her ſelf, like a <hi>bloody</hi> Victim on the <hi>Altar</hi> of the Croſs. For as the <hi>Son</hi> of God ought not to paſs from the Boſom of his <hi>Father,</hi> into that of a Virgin <hi>Mother,</hi> and to make himſelf Man without <hi>her Conſent;</hi> ſo neither ought he, neither would he be deſtin'd to the <hi>Death,</hi> which was to make us <hi>Immortal,</hi> but by the <hi>Conſent</hi> of this his <hi>Mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If then She generouſly executes the thing in the World, which is the moſt <hi>difficult</hi> to her, the depriving her ſelf of the <hi>Object</hi> of all her Delights, conſenting to the Death of her <hi>only</hi> Son, an Action na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally contrary to the Love of ſuch a Mother: If She quits the part of a <hi>Lover,</hi> to become a <hi>Believer;</hi> and a Mothers <hi>Affections,</hi> to perform <hi>Obedience</hi> to God; if laſtly, <hi>Juſtice</hi> carries her beyond <hi>Love;</hi> how
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51732:17"/>can it be, that the Virgin <hi>obliged</hi> by Divine and Humane Laws, to Honour her Mother, ſhould not employ <hi>all</hi> the Artifices of her Love, and <hi>all</hi> the efforts of her Power, to make of St. <hi>Ann</hi> a true Sanctuary of <hi>all</hi> Graces?</p>
               <p>The Grace to conſult the Judgment of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> is a <hi>Participation of Divine Nature;</hi> the Virgin therefore having the <hi>Plenitude</hi> of this in her Boſom, for the <hi>Communication</hi> of it to Souls, and being not only bleſſed among all Women, but the very <hi>Spring</hi> of all Bleſſings; what part ought She to give to her <hi>Mother?</hi> A Duty which further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>The Obedience of the Virgin to St.</hi> ANN. <hi>The third Reaſon of her Prerogatives.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF from this, that the Son of God was well pleaſed to ſubmit his <hi>impeccable</hi> Will, to that of the Virgin; a good Conſequence is drawn, how <hi>Innocent</hi> and <hi>Straight</hi> ought that Rule to be, which gave Law to the Son of God?</p>
               <p>So to ſee this little Virgin <hi>impeccable</hi> by <hi>Grace,</hi> as her Son was by <hi>Nature,</hi> at the Feet of St. <hi>Ann,</hi> to take the Inſtructions and Exerciſes of her Mother, has one not a juſt Motive to believe the Innocence, and the Rectitude of the Affections and Paſſions of this Holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who ought to <hi>regulate</hi> thoſe of her Daugther, who was the <hi>moſt perfect</hi> of all Creatures? The <hi>Perſonal</hi> Union ſet a part, is as much remov'd from the leaſt ſpot of Sin, as the Sun from Darkneſs and Obſcurity; and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> took ſo high a flight in the Praiſes of the Virgin, that he got out of Sight, ſaying, That he advanc'd nothing that exceeded her Merit, by calling her the <hi>Form of God;</hi> that is, tho there be no Miracle in the World like to the Mercies of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and thoſe of his <hi>Mother</hi> be but little <hi>Rays</hi> in Compariſon of this <hi>Sun;</hi> he was pleas'd to frame as it were an <hi>Idea,</hi> on which he caſt his Eyes, to <hi>mark</hi> upon <hi>his</hi> Soul the beautiful <hi>Lines</hi> of the excellent Practices of Virtue, which he ſaw in his <hi>Mother,</hi> to the end one might ſee in the <hi>Son,</hi> as it were a <hi>lively Image,</hi> and <hi>Expreſſion</hi> of the rare Virtues of the <hi>Mother;</hi> or elſe, and <hi>rather</hi> this brave Title of <hi>Form of God,</hi> means that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> had a deſign, that as in the Looking-Glaſs, the <hi>Image</hi> of his Face is ſeen, who <hi>locks</hi> into it, and as Wax receives the Form and Figure of the <hi>Seal,</hi> which is <hi>imprinted</hi> on it; ev'n ſo, the Holy Virgin was <hi>marked</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51732:17"/>with the <hi>Seal</hi> of the Divine Perfections of <hi>Jeſus;</hi> and She has <hi>repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented</hi> them in her ſelf after a very excellent manner.</p>
               <p>So nothing is advanc'd concerning the <hi>Merits</hi> of St. <hi>Ann,</hi> which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crues not to the Honour and Glory of her <hi>Daughter,</hi> by calling her the true <hi>Form of the Virgin,</hi> and by ſaying She had ſuch Accumulation of <hi>Perfections,</hi> that to ſee the Holy <hi>Virgin</hi> practice thoſe Virtues, which came ſo <hi>near</hi> thoſe of her Mother, one would reaſonably judg that St. <hi>Ann</hi> might ſerve as an <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Model</hi> to the holy Actions of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, if they had not been otherwiſe more Holy in proportion to the Grace of the <hi>Mother of God,</hi> which heightned them.</p>
               <p>To what degree of Sanctity ought St. <hi>Ann</hi> to be exalted, who ſo lively <hi>expreſſed,</hi> and ſo perfectly <hi>repreſented</hi> in her ſelf, the Virtues of the <hi>Virgin;</hi> and whoſe rare Qualities might be the <hi>Idea</hi>'s and <hi>Patterns</hi> of thoſe of this her ſo worthy a Daughter. But</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>The Glory of</hi> JESUS CHRIST. <hi>The fourth Reaſon of the Prerogatives of St.</hi> ANN</head>
               <p>REquires that St. <hi>Ann</hi> ſhould be ſuch, to be his worthy Grand-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For if the <hi>Meſſias</hi> from the time that he prepar'd his Birth for the World, and put his firſt diſpoſals and deſigns in <hi>Abraham,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd Innocence and Sanctity from him to merit this favour; muſt he not deſire thoſe incomparably <hi>greater</hi> in St. <hi>Ann,</hi> according to the <hi>meaſure</hi> that She more nearly approach'd his Blood. The Holy Virgin then ſeeing the Glory of her Son engag'd, and the Sanctity of her Mother to enter into the Intereſts of the <hi>Incarnate Word</hi> her Son, muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he not have made St. <hi>Ann</hi> a Work of Grace worthy of the <hi>Admiration</hi> of Angels, and of the <hi>Adoration</hi> of Men?</p>
               <p>And if elſewhere, in the deſigns of the eternal Providence, and in the Language of Scripture, <hi>Names</hi> ſerve for a mark of <hi>Offices,</hi> and <hi>Offices</hi> are the meaſures of <hi>Merits;</hi> St. <hi>Ann</hi> having been choſen in the Idea's of eternal Predeſtination to be the <hi>Grand-Mother</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> ought not this ſtep to comprehend as many Excellencies as demonſtrate the Sublimeneſs of this Saints Perfections? There need be us'd only the <hi>Dignity</hi> of her <hi>Name</hi> of Grandmother of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> An Argument which the Apoſtle uſes to prove the Pre-eminences of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> above the <hi>Angelical</hi> Natures; for that he was the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> The <hi>Dignity</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in St. <hi>Ann,</hi> that having enter'd by the <hi>Conception</hi> and <hi>Nativity</hi> of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51732:18"/>
                  <hi>Virgin,</hi> into the Oeconomy of the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> and into the ſtate of the <hi>Hypoſtatical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> She was by this her Daughter, exalted into ſo daz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a <hi>Throne</hi> of Glory, that there is only above it, the <hi>Trinity</hi> of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created Perſons, the <hi>Humanity</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and the Holineſs of her Daughter, <hi>Mother of God;</hi> leaving below her Greatneſs all other cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <hi>Eminencies;</hi> without doubt St. <hi>Ann</hi> ought to expect ſuch a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence from the Queen of Virtues, and the worthy Mother of the King of Virtues, the Virgin. It remains now to ſee</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>The Internal Perfections of St.</hi> ANN</head>
               <p>WIth Relation to which we muſt Sacrifice <hi>cloſed</hi> Eyes, like thoſe who ador'd the <hi>Fortune</hi> of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and in the Extaſis of our Hearts, and in the humble Sentiments that carry our Souls to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs our <hi>Impotencies,</hi> to acknowledg the <hi>Merits</hi> and <hi>Virtues</hi> of her, who bore in her barren Womb the firſt fruits of our <hi>Redemption,</hi> and who nouriſh'd with her Milk the Fruit of all <hi>Benediction;</hi> let us be content to ſay, That as the faireſt Flower of the Virgins Crown was the Meriting her exalted Dignity of <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> ſo that of St. <hi>Ann</hi> is, that God gave to her Merits, this glorious Advantage of conceiving in her Bowels a Daughter, whoſe Conception <hi>without Sin,</hi> and Birth full of Honour; effected the <hi>Re-eſtabliſhment</hi> of the Univerſe. Merits which were</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Her Prayers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOR tho God in the Decrees of his <hi>Providence</hi> be <hi>reſolv'd</hi> to beſtow certain Graces on ſome Perſons; he nevertheleſs <hi>determin'd</hi> before the World not to grant them but to thoſe who ask for them; and in the everlaſting Preparation of ſuch Favours, their <hi>Prayers</hi> are included either as <hi>Cauſes</hi> or <hi>Means</hi> of obtaining.</p>
               <p>Hence he would have us <hi>ask</hi> the very things which he is <hi>reſolv'd</hi> to <hi>give</hi> us, as we muſt <hi>open</hi> our Eyes to <hi>receive</hi> the light of the Sun, and obſerve ſome <hi>Formalities</hi> to obtain the Graces of a Prince. Thus God having in his eternal Predeſtination prepar'd this incomparable Benefit for St. <hi>Ann,</hi> to be <hi>Mother</hi> of the <hi>Mother of the Word Incarnate;</hi> he would that She ſhould acquire this ineffable Treaſure by her Tears and Vows;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51732:18"/>that ſo her <hi>Merit</hi> might enter into the Execution of this everlaſting <hi>Counſel.</hi> St. <hi>Ann</hi> therefore having been above twenty years in a State of Barrenneſs with him whom God had given her for a Husband, St. <hi>Joachim,</hi> was in Affliction to ſee her ſelf without a Child, who might blot out the Reproach which She met with in the Company of other Ladies; requeſted daily from Heaven, with a Countenance of <hi>Grief,</hi> a <hi>Remedy</hi> for her <hi>Diſgrace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But there is nothing which ſo much <hi>contracted</hi> her Heart, as the Confuſion and Shame which the High-Prieſt <hi>Iſſachar</hi> one day put her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, as She went according to her Cuſtom to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> at the Solemnity of one of the great Feaſts of the year, where in face of all the World, he reproach'd her of Raſhneſs and Boldneſs, to appear with the reſt, She who bore the <hi>marks</hi> of Gods <hi>Malediction,</hi> with which being troubled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the quick, and not knowing from whom to receive Conſolation, She had recourſe to God with Supplication to take from her this <hi>Reproach,</hi> and with Promiſe to Conſecrate to him the Fruit which he ſhould pleaſe to give her; and not daring to preſent her ſelf any more openly to the World, She threw her ſelf into a Solitude and Retreat, which ſhut up all Avenues to Company, having no other Companions but her Thoughts, and her Affections for Heaven. In this loneſome place, where She was wholly attentive to her God, wholly fixed and bent in Spirit and Will to <hi>him,</hi> to conſider <hi>his</hi> Greatneſs, and admire <hi>his</hi> Perfections, and where She did every day <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>heroical</hi> Acts of Love, and of <hi>Conformity</hi> to the Divine Pleaſure, of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> of <hi>Adoration</hi> and <hi>Glorification,</hi> and other Virtues; not to ſpeak of the Sublime Operations of the <hi>Myſtical Life,</hi> to which God had exalted her, and which all the Words of Men are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot able to explicate.</p>
               <p>But where in recompence of her <hi>Introverſions</hi> and <hi>Recollections,</hi> there was happily fulfill'd in her the Prophecy in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35. in favour of the Souls that retire from their <hi>Commerce</hi> with the World, to be <hi>buſied</hi> only with God; for as much as She receiv'd unſpeakable Joys in her Deſert; and that her Retreat was to her a Spring of living Delights. For the heavenly Angel came to viſit her on the beginning of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and brought to her the happy, and the fortunate News from God, of a Daughter, which ſhould be named <hi>Mary,</hi> which ſhould not only cauſe Joy to her, but ſhould likewiſe be the happineſs of infinite others, ſince ſhe was to be the <hi>Mother</hi> of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> promiſed in the Law; and to collect in her ſelf the Riches of <hi>Libanus</hi> and <hi>Carmel,</hi> which are the Fruitfulneſs of a Mother, and the Integrity of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin in the ſame Spirit.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51732:19"/>
               <p>And, as has been ſaid, ſo God repair'd with an exceeding advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by <hi>himſelf,</hi> and by the abundance of <hi>his Graces,</hi> all the Loſſes which this Soul ſuffer'd, retired from the Contentments and Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of all Creatures, and made her Solitude like <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> Mirth and Joy are found <hi>here,</hi> and Praiſes are <hi>here</hi> retain'd; for having ſeen her. <hi>Barrenneſs</hi> follow'd with the Birth of a Daughter, who is the <hi>Treaſure</hi> of Heaven and Earth, and who gave her a <hi>God</hi> for <hi>Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> O the Noble Fruit of the <hi>Prayer</hi> of St. <hi>Ann! Mary,</hi> who is the Wonder of <hi>Nature,</hi> the Prodigy of <hi>Grace,</hi> and the Miracle of <hi>Glory.</hi> After her Prayer comes</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Her Humility.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF <hi>Prayer</hi> be in the Opinion of the Fathers, an <hi>Elevation</hi> of the Soul to <hi>God,</hi> as of a <hi>Vapour</hi> from the <hi>Earth</hi> to <hi>Heaven;</hi> it is neceſſary Firſt, That as the <hi>Vapour</hi> is <hi>elevated</hi> from the <hi>Earth</hi> by the Rays of the <hi>Sun,</hi> attracting it with its <hi>heat,</hi> and ſubtilizing it by taking away its <hi>gravitating</hi> Quality derived from the <hi>Earth,</hi> the place of its Origine; juſt ſo the <hi>Prayer</hi> of St. <hi>Ann,</hi> that it might be <hi>elevated</hi> as high as <hi>Gods</hi> Throne, was directed thitherward in little <hi>Fumes</hi> which the <hi>heat</hi> of Divine <hi>Love</hi> excited in her, <hi>purifying</hi> whatever ſhe had of <hi>Earth,</hi> that her Soul might have only the Affections and Sentiments of <hi>Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, That as the <hi>Vapour</hi> being in the <hi>Middle</hi> Region of the Air, melts and <hi>falls back</hi> towards the <hi>Earth,</hi> as if the <hi>Sun</hi> by its Rays would conſtrain it to <hi>return to,</hi> and <hi>know</hi> its firſt Principle; juſt ſo the <hi>Prayer</hi> which the Tongue and Heart of St. <hi>Ann</hi> had ſent up into the Boſom of God, ought by the Divine Ray to be abaſed and <hi>reflected</hi> into the Conſideration of one's <hi>Nothing,</hi> and to return to the <hi>Earth</hi> by Sentiments of <hi>Humility;</hi> but ſuch as ſhould bring along with them the Showers and the Dews of <hi>Jeſus</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> and which ſhould fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilize the <hi>Human Nature</hi> with a <hi>God Man,</hi> and with the <hi>Mother of God:</hi> An excellent Rule of Prayer in the <hi>Approaches</hi> and <hi>Fervours,</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nions</hi> and <hi>Exaltations</hi> of one Being to <hi>deſcend</hi> back into <hi>Meanneſs,</hi> and the Meditation that one <hi>is</hi> Nothing, that one <hi>is worth</hi> Nothing, that one <hi>can do</hi> Nothing, that <hi>one merits</hi> nothing from God.</p>
               <p>Which is the Reaſon perhaps why the High Prieſt ſprinkled thoſe who offered Sacrifices, with Aſhes mixt with Water, to advertiſe them that they were nothing but <hi>dead Earth,</hi> uncapable of Conſiſtence
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51732:19"/>and Motion without the Favours of <hi>Heaven;</hi> and that they ought to be of <hi>Abrahams</hi> mind, who ſaid, I will appear before my Lord, <hi>duſt and aſhes as I am.</hi> Hence it follows that we ought to hope for the Grace of God, and <hi>Supernatural</hi> Powers.</p>
               <p>It is in theſe <hi>Valleys</hi> of <hi>mean eſteem</hi> of ones ſelf, ſays <hi>David,</hi> that God makes the Fountains of his Favours, and the Waters of his Grace to flow; and not upon the <hi>Mountains</hi> and Spirits of <hi>Preſumption,</hi> that approach the Temples and the Altars, with Head and Face lifted up before <hi>him,</hi> in whoſe Preſence the <hi>Angels</hi> tremble, and the <hi>Seraphims</hi> ſink down into the loweſt depths with Reverence; and before whom; ſays St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> if thou wilt humble thy ſelf, the bait of thy <hi>Humility</hi> attracts him, and he is <hi>conſtrain'd</hi> to deſcend from his <hi>Father</hi>'s Boſom into <hi>thine;</hi> thou <hi>poſſeſſeſt</hi> him, and doſt with him after the Inclination of <hi>thy will:</hi> But if <hi>vain glory</hi> accompany thy Prayer, thou findeſt a God who has Thunder in his hand to deſtroy thee. 'Twas in theſe vallies of mean eſteem of her ſelf, the Prayer of St. <hi>Ann</hi> found Forces, and the grant of her Requeſts. Her Third Merit was</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP X. <hi>Her Generous Confidence in God's Providence.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Earth, in my Opinion, is the <hi>Nobleſt,</hi> tho the <hi>laſt</hi> of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, becauſe being not able to act of <hi>its ſelf,</hi> this ſtate gives it ſo much Sympathy with the <hi>Sun,</hi> that it becomes fruitful through the favour of his Beams in all kinds of Production: So it is a very <hi>glorious</hi> Weakneſs, and <hi>powerful</hi> Impotence, for an humble Soul to acknowledg her <hi>Miſeries</hi> and her <hi>Nothing:</hi> Since God beholding this <hi>Void,</hi> he immediately repleniſhes it with his <hi>Grace;</hi> for where the <hi>Creature</hi> is not, there is the <hi>Creator</hi> preſently found; and where <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> leaves us, there the <hi>Godhead</hi> enters by a Conſequence as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the Order of <hi>Grace,</hi> as in that of <hi>Nature,</hi> the Air immediately fills thoſe places which it finds <hi>void.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as God has extraordinary Graces that reward <hi>Humility,</hi> and exalt it from its meanneſs into which it ſeems plunged; among others there is a generouſneſs of Heart which the <hi>humble</hi> Soul draws from the great Confidence ſhe puts in this, that an Infinite Wiſdom both <hi>knows,</hi> and <hi>is able;</hi> and <hi>will</hi> help her; triumphing over her Miſeries and Weakneſſes; and being to her what her <hi>Soul</hi> is to her Body, or the <hi>Heaven</hi> to the Earth.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51732:20"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Confidence</hi> in God, which comprehends all the moſt diſtant degrees of nature in a moſt ſimple Unity, unites theſe two Contrarieties, to believe that we can <hi>do nothing,</hi> and that we can <hi>do every thing.</hi> That we are able to do nothing of our <hi>own</hi> ſtrength, and that we can do eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing in virtue of the <hi>Divine</hi> Arm on which we relye. Thus when <hi>Humility</hi> has made us diffident of our ſelves, we ought to raiſe our Courages by an holy and invincible <hi>Faith,</hi> that may make us brave all the Diſgraces and Difficulties of the World, looking to this all-ſeeing eye, and all-powerful Arm, who has a heart readier to give to us, than ours to ask or receive.</p>
               <p>Such was the Prayer of S. <hi>Ann,</hi> animated with a lively Faith, not only a <hi>general</hi> one, which made her believe that God to whom ſhe pray'd was all-powerful, and all-good, and had a Paternal Providence, and an infinite love for her; but a <hi>particular</hi> faith that this gracious God would grant her the deſir'd Grace, according to the Pattern of another <hi>Ann</hi> the Mother of <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 1. Concerning whom the Sacred Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle pronounces that after the Prayer which ſhe made to obtain a Son, ſhe was no more agitated by any waves of Inquietude; but was left in a conſtant evenneſs, and a perfect tranquility of mind, as if ſhe already had the thing ſhe pray'd for, ſays St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> of the firſt <hi>Anna,</hi> and felt the Babe form'd and ſtirring in her womb, inaſmuch as ſhe had beg'd it with a ſpirit not wavering, undoubtful of ſucceſs, but with an entire confidence, and an unſhaken perſwaſion that ſhe ſhould obtain. 'Tis thus, ſays St. <hi>Thomas</hi> 2a. 2ae. <hi>Q.</hi> 83. that as Charity makes our Prayer <hi>meritorious,</hi> Confidence makes it <hi>impetratorious,</hi> or effectual. Thus it is that thoſe great <hi>Courages</hi> who fully <hi>confide</hi> in God, glorifie him more by the Noble and high Sentiments that they have of him, than a Million of <hi>narrow</hi> hearts, to whom all ſeems loſt as ſoon as they ſee any thing fail 'em, and themſelves left by ſome one of theſe <hi>broken reeds,</hi> the Creatures on which they rely'd.</p>
               <p>Thus it is that St. <hi>Baſil</hi> in his 20th. <hi>Orat. de Principatu</hi> exalts <hi>Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> as much as <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> and ſays, It's no more lawful to place it any where elſe than in God, than to preſent the <hi>Cult</hi> which the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice contains, to any other than him. To this I add, that as the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour we give to God in <hi>Sacrifice</hi> is very great by reaſon of the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation</hi> we there make of acknowledging him for our <hi>Soveraign:</hi> So that which he receives from us by <hi>Confidence,</hi> is wonderful, inaſmuch as it is like an Oath of <hi>Fealty,</hi> and an <hi>Homage</hi> whereby we oblige our ſelves to be willing to <hi>depend</hi> on him <hi>alone, avowing</hi> his infinite boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and infallible verity, and <hi>renouncing</hi> every other hold which we
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51732:20"/>might have but him, which is very honourable to him; and it is thus that our Saint by the vigour and firmneſs of her <hi>Faith merited</hi> the greateſt Grace in the World next to the <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Maternity,</hi> that is, to bear in her Womb the <hi>Virgin,</hi> who was to be the <hi>Mother of God,</hi> and to have for <hi>Grandſon,</hi> and embrace in her Arms no leſs than him who has <hi>God</hi> for his <hi>Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After theſe Preeminences of this great <hi>Saint,</hi> we have nothing to do but to contribute our <hi>Homages</hi> by Invocation of her <hi>Powers,</hi> and the <hi>imitation</hi> of her <hi>Vertues.</hi> As for,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Her Credit and Power in Heaven.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF St. <hi>Ann</hi> next to the <hi>Virgin</hi> be the <hi>neareſt</hi> to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and has a greater ſhare of him than any of all the Saints in the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> which is the cauſe of the Crowns they wear; it is eaſie to conclude, that this <hi>Proximity</hi> has given her the moſt eminent of <hi>Paradice,</hi> as wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter partakes more of the qualities of its Spring, the <hi>nearer</hi> it is to it; and that her <hi>Credit</hi> is parallel to her <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> which the better to comprehend, it is neceſſary to remember how all Gods creatures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the productions of his Goodneſs, by the Being which he gave them as an <hi>extract</hi> of his own, he would have them to <hi>rejoyn</hi> again to him as to their <hi>final,</hi> as well as <hi>efficient</hi> cauſe, placing this Perfection in this <hi>Reunion</hi> and <hi>Return</hi> to their Principle.</p>
               <p>Now according to the Doctrine of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> in his Book of the <hi>Humility of Chriſt,</hi> his Will was to recall to himſelf <hi>middle</hi> things by the <hi>high,</hi> and <hi>low</hi> ones by the <hi>middle;</hi> and he makes uſe of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to gather together, and <hi>reunite</hi> by <hi>him</hi> whatever is in Heaven or in Earth; and this <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> makes uſe in the firſt place of the <hi>Holy Virgin</hi> as the neareſt ally'd, then of ſome Perſons of Election and <hi>near</hi> approach to the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> the Principle of all <hi>Sanctification;</hi> upon this account therefore St. <hi>Ann</hi> was to have the <hi>next</hi> rank to her Daughter, and muſt approach neareſt after her in the <hi>Sanctity</hi> of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> and in <hi>Grace,</hi> which is with St. <hi>James</hi> a quality wholly Divine, defending from the <hi>Father of Lights into our Souls,</hi> and muſt come there firſt by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> then by the <hi>Virgin,</hi> and after that by St. <hi>Ann;</hi> conſequently in our Indigencies and Needs we muſt addreſs our ſelves by St. <hi>ANN</hi> to the <hi>Virgin,</hi> and by the <hi>Virgin</hi> to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to <hi>God</hi> his Father, who can refuſe nothing to his <hi>Son,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:51732:21"/>no more than <hi>he</hi> can to his <hi>Mother,</hi> or <hi>ſhe</hi> to <hi>hers</hi> who is St. <hi>Ann.</hi> And as St. <hi>Gertrude,</hi> a Virgin of an incomparable Piety and Glory of the <hi>French</hi> Scepter, ſaw one day in an extacy Angels who deſcended from Heaven, and who in the midſt of the Quire where the ſinging was, brought a moſt reſplendent <hi>Throne</hi> of Glory, in the which the H. Virgin being ſeated, like a Queen full of Majeſty, received the Prayers of all the Nuns who approacht this Throne, and fulfilled their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
               <p>It muſt be ſaid that this <hi>Throne</hi> was the Glorious St. <hi>Ann,</hi> in which <hi>Jeſus</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> are ſet down; and if we would obtain any Grace whatever, we muſt proſtrate our ſelves before this <hi>Throne of Grace, Ann</hi> being rightly interpreted <hi>Grace,</hi> and go thither with Confidence and Fervour. But above all, with</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>The Imitation of her Virtues,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY which we revere her <hi>Sanctity,</hi> as by our Prayers we humbly acknowledg her <hi>Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this the whole end and fruit that God would have by <hi>Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Cults</hi> toward this <hi>Saint,</hi> and the ſole means which thoſe Souls who carry this fair Name of <hi>Ann,</hi> have to poſſeſs it with advantage.</p>
               <p>For as God ſeeing that we are but impotent and wretched Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, having no Preſent worthy to approach his <hi>Throne,</hi> and to be offered to him, deſires from our Weakneſs only the <hi>ſanctification</hi> of his <hi>Name,</hi> which is perform'd by <hi>Holineſs</hi> in our Manners, and <hi>Innocence</hi> in our Lives.</p>
               <p>It is alſo this his Grandmother deſires from the Souls who carry her <hi>Name,</hi> ſignifying a Spring of <hi>Grace,</hi> that their hearts be always repleniſh'd <hi>with it,</hi> for that elſe they would poſſeſs it but by injuſtice and violence; and this would be to have a <hi>ſplendid</hi> name in appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, accompanied with very ill circumſtances; and to fall into the reproach of a <hi>Judas,</hi> a word which ſignifies <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> but who was notwithſtanding the <hi>perfidious</hi> Traytor of his Maſter; or of an <hi>Abſolom,</hi> That is to ſay, the <hi>Peace of his Father,</hi> and who was yet his <hi>torment</hi> and his <hi>ſcourge;</hi> or of a <hi>Solomon, amabilis Deo,</hi> the beloved of God, by whom he was nevertheleſs <hi>hated</hi> for his impurities. This, laſtly, would be to be a <hi>Capernaum, Ager penitentiae,</hi> the Field of penitence, a Town which was yet ſo obſtinate, and which car'd ſo little to do
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51732:21"/>Penance, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in St. <hi>Luke</hi> ſwore its deſtruction.</p>
               <p>A Name then ſo favourable, and ſo full of Grace as <hi>Ann,</hi> ought to furniſh continual matters of Virtue to the Souls who have the honour to bear it, if they but never ſo little permit their thoughts to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on it; and this obliges them <hi>particularly,</hi> as it <hi>generally</hi> obliges all Chriſtians,</p>
               <p>To have always holy <hi>Alliances</hi> and Sacred ties with God the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of <hi>Grace,</hi> to follow always the guidances and motives of <hi>Grace,</hi> but eſpecially to practice ſuch of <hi>her</hi> Virtues as <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> knows to be moſt convenient for our condition; as among other, <hi>her</hi> ſolitudes and <hi>her</hi> retreats, ſo to make you often ſeen to God and to your ſelf: For it is in the <hi>Hives</hi> that the Bees make <hi>ſecretly</hi> their Honey, and the <hi>Silk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worms</hi> make their Silk within their <hi>Cells;</hi> Nature forms the King of <hi>Metals</hi> in ſilence, in the <hi>Caverns</hi> of the Earth, out of the noiſe and ſight of Men: The <hi>Manna</hi> fell during the <hi>reſt</hi> and <hi>calm</hi> of the night, not with Storm or Tempeſt, but gently and without tumult, as the <hi>dew</hi> which is ſoftly and without ſhew tranſpir'd into the boſom of the Earth.</p>
               <p>It is not in the hurry of the World, in the noiſe of Houſe-keeping, in the Inquietude of Cares, in the turmoils of an active and a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Life, but in the <hi>ſeparation</hi> from every thing in the <hi>bottom</hi> of the Soul, in <hi>Tranquility,</hi> the <hi>diſengagement</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> of the Spirit in the <hi>recollection</hi> and <hi>ſolitude</hi> of the Heart, where the Holy Spirit ſheds abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly its Graces, to prepare a Soul, of whom he deſigns to make an <hi>inſtrument</hi> of his <hi>Wonders,</hi> as he did of St. <hi>Ann.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is in this Sanctuary that this <hi>hidden Manna</hi> is found, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. that is given to the Souls Triumphant over the World, which is no other thing but an ineffable <hi>Conſolation</hi> begot from a very inward and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual <hi>Inclination</hi> towards God, with a <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>reliſh</hi> of his Truths and Greatneſs, better apprehended by <hi>Experience</hi> than by <hi>Knowledg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is in the Quietude of this <hi>Divine Genter</hi> and <hi>Fund,</hi> that there is taſted this kind of Prayer which you deſire, Holy Souls, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not ſo much in that which is <hi>ours</hi> in functions and uſes of <hi>our</hi> Powers, but in that which is <hi>God's,</hi> and in the infuſion of <hi>his</hi> Graces, where through a <hi>full ſilence</hi> of the Soul, which is a denudation of <hi>Thoughts</hi> in the Underſtanding, and of <hi>Affections</hi> in the Will; the ſole <hi>Maſter of Hearts</hi> ſpeaks and brings nothing thither but that ſole diſpoſition of Reſpect and Submiſſion to the moſt pure, moſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and moſt inward action of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncreated Spirit</hi> in <hi>ours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is <hi>here</hi> you ſhall not only be able to carry your Hopes beyond the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51732:22"/>Forces, and to caſt your filial and amorous Confidences into the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of God's Arm, and into the Sweetneſs of the Love which he hath for you; but ſhall alſo adjuſt you to your Rule, which can't fail, that after the requeſt of ſome Grace from God, you may have your Spirit at reſt, and <hi>depoſited</hi> in that of God, to wait for, with Patience and Silence, as <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſays, the Salvation of God.</p>
               <p>It is <hi>here,</hi> That after the Pattern of St. <hi>Ann,</hi> you give up your ſelf to the entire Conſummation of the moſt holy Will, and moſt adorable Deſigns, which God has had from Eternity upon you, and upon each moment of your Life. And it is <hi>here,</hi> that your Soul appearing quite <hi>naked</hi> before him, ſubmits her ſelf to him with abſolute Reſignation of <hi>Spirit,</hi> of <hi>Senſe,</hi> of <hi>Taſt,</hi> and of all manner of <hi>Satifaction,</hi> deſiring nought but <hi>God's</hi> only Good, and the Intereſt of his Glory; breathing forth theſe Words from all your Heart, I caſt my ſelf at the Mercy of the Love which you have for me, O my God. I am the Object of the Vigilance and the Affection of a God. It's enough for me that thou takeſt the Title of my <hi>Father,</hi> to make me ſee that thy <hi>Power</hi> is inſeparable from thy <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> that I ought to expect thence all the good that ſhall be to thy Glory, and my Salvation, which is whatever I muſt; that all the preſent deſires of God be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht on me: I am content and indifferent to all, for Scarcity or Abundance, to Act or to Suffer, for Obtaining or Refuſing, Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Deſolation, <hi>Calvary</hi> or <hi>Thabor.</hi> I offer my ſelf to all as a <hi>pure Capacity</hi> of God to his deſigns.</p>
               <p>It is <hi>here,</hi> laſtly, That you muſt ſupplicate him to lead you into <hi>Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and all other <hi>Exerciſes</hi> of Life; either <hi>retired</hi> or <hi>ſecular,</hi> by the way he has ordained for you, whether of <hi>Conformity,</hi> which is a total <hi>Subjection,</hi> and reſolute <hi>Dependance</hi> of <hi>your</hi> Will <hi>on</hi> the <hi>Divine</hi> Will in all Events and Occurrences, however diſpleaſing and irkſom, comforting your ſelf in your very misfortune, or diſgrace, of ſeeing you an Object of the Divine <hi>Severity,</hi> if it tend to his Glory. Or</p>
               <p>Of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> which adds to the other an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of <hi>your</hi> Will <hi>with</hi> the <hi>Divine,</hi> which takes away all repugnance and difficulty, and brings an appetite and longing deſire of what God <hi>Wills,</hi> and carries the Soul to <hi>will</hi> it, for this reaſon only, that God is therewith contented, and deſires it; and which cauſes that in all our internal and external <hi>Operations,</hi> the Soul be in a moment <hi>united</hi> to God, to know in theſe his good pleaſure, and to put the ſame immediately into Practice: Or laſtly,</p>
               <p>Of <hi>Deformity,</hi> which <hi>unites</hi> the <hi>Will</hi> by ſuch an efficacy of Love to the <hi>Divine,</hi> that the Soul no longer <hi>feels</hi> or <hi>perceives</hi> her ſelf, than as if She
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51732:22"/>were really <hi>no more</hi> in being; and in her Manners and Actions, only <hi>feels</hi> in her ſelf the <hi>uncreated Will,</hi> by an intire <hi>Transformation</hi> made her <hi>own,</hi> as we ſee a little drop of <hi>Water</hi> preſently take the Colour, Taſt, and Nature of <hi>Wine;</hi> and a piece of <hi>Iron</hi> thrown into the Fire, quit in ſome manner, the <hi>Form</hi> and Appearance of Iron, to take that of <hi>Fire;</hi> and as the <hi>Air,</hi> which is penetrated by the Rays of the <hi>Sun,</hi> ſeems not ſo much to be <hi>enlightned,</hi> as to be <hi>light</hi> it ſelf.</p>
               <p>By theſe <hi>three ways,</hi> or even any <hi>one</hi> of theſe, you'l <hi>worthily</hi> Honour the Greatneſs and <hi>Prerogatives,</hi> and <hi>certainly</hi> implore the <hi>Favours</hi> of the <hi>Great St.</hi> ANN.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Prayer to St.</hi> ANN.</head>
               <p>O Great Saint, <hi>in</hi> Honour <hi>of Gods regarding and exalting You in his Eternity, to theſe moſt high and ſublime Eſtates of</hi> Mother <hi>of the</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>of</hi> God, <hi>and</hi> Grandmother <hi>of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And in</hi> Union <hi>of all the Graees which were given you in conſequence of theſe; of the</hi> Sanctity <hi>of your Soul, of your moſt profound</hi> Humility, <hi>of your perfect</hi> Reſignation, <hi>of your eminent</hi> Devotion, <hi>of your</hi> Silence <hi>and</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, <hi>of the tenderneſs of your</hi> Loves <hi>towards your</hi> Daughter <hi>and</hi> Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>of your continual</hi> Application <hi>of Mind toward theſe two</hi> Divine Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; <hi>of all the Offices of</hi> Grandmother, <hi>which you were worthy to render to</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>in Honour of this, that he hath ſo ſtrongly ti'd you in</hi> Blood, Spirit <hi>and</hi> Grace, <hi>to his</hi> Hypoſtatical Union.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In</hi> Adoration <hi>of all the Virtues of your Life, and of the laſt Breath, in which You gave up the Spirit in the ſtate of final Grace, conſummated in the hand of your Grandſon, and your God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In</hi> Homage <hi>of the Right and Power which you had of Mother over your Daughter, and of Grandmother over her Son, and of their Submiſſions and Reverences which they render'd You.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In</hi> Acknowledgment, <hi>laſtly, of this, That you were not only of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily which Jeſus Chriſt came to eſtabliſh upon Earth, but even Mother and Head of this Family, and looking on Jeſus, as making a part of your Family.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O glorious</hi> Saint, <hi>aſſociate me to this worthy</hi> Family, <hi>bind and unite my Soul to</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>and that I may be wholly</hi> his; <hi>ſince you touch</hi> him <hi>ſo near, as there is none but</hi> Mary <hi>betwixt you and</hi> Him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O, I believe, That in Virtue of this great Communication of Love and Grace, which was between you, and the</hi> Author, <hi>and the</hi> Mother <hi>of</hi> Grace, <hi>that you have Right and Power in Heav'n, to give Souls to</hi> Jeſus, and <hi>to</hi> Mary.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:51732:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>O my Soveraign, next to</hi> Jeſus <hi>and</hi> Mary, <hi>give them my Soul; I yield and reſign to You all the Power that I have over my ſelf; I put under Your Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Protection all the Moments and Motions of my Life, and all the Perſons that compoſe my Family, which henceforward I will call Yours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly, My all-dear Mother and Miſtreſs, for the laſt Grace, I beg of You, That as You had always your Eyes upon the Divine Face of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>and Your Heart in his with Burnings and Flames which he enkindled with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you when you had the Honour of Kiſſing and Embracing him, a time which ſo continued to encreaſe each moment, that at laſt it put a Period to Your Life, when not being able to ſupport the effort of it, You happily, and by an exceſs and languiſhing of Love, expir'd in the hands of Your Daughter, and in the Kiſſes of Your Grandſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O that You would juſt ſo aſſiſt me in the Paſſage and Deciſive Moment of mine Eternity, and obtain for me an happy Death under the Protection of the</hi> Virgin, <hi>and in the Grace of</hi> Jeſus.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="fre" type="approbation">
            <head>Approbation.</head>
            <p>Nous ſoubſignez Docteurs en Theologie de la Faculté de Paris, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifions avoir leu, &amp; examiné ce Livre Intitulé Les Grandeurs de Sainte Anne, dedié a la Reyne par les Filles de Saint Joſeph, auquel n'avons rien trouvé que de conforme à l'Egliſe Apoſtolique &amp; Romaine. Au contraire l'avons eſtimé digne d'eſtre mis en lumiere, comme tref-utile pour entretenir la Devotion a Sainte Anne. En foy de quoy nous avons ſegne. Fait a Paris ce dixieſme Juillet Mil ſix cens quarante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trois.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Vincent Jude. C. Bourlon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="approbation">
            <head>The Approbation in Engliſh.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>We the Doctors in Divinity underwritten, of the Faculty of</hi> Paris, <hi>do cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, That we have read and examined this Book, intituled, The Prerogatives of St.</hi> Ann, <hi>dedicated to the Queen by the Maids of St.</hi> Joſeph, <hi>wherein we have found nothing but what is conformable to the Apoſtolick and</hi> Roman <hi>Church. On the contrary, we have thought it worthy to be Publiſhed as very uſeful to maintain the Devotion to St.</hi> Ann. <hi>In Faith whereof we have ſigned. Given at</hi> Paris <hi>this</hi> 10th <hi>of</hi> July, 1643.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Vincent Jude. C. Bourlon.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51732:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
